<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spiritual flovvers for saints and sinners. Gathered out of the garden of the sacred scriptures, and writings of men famous in their generations. / By Robert Port minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Port, Robert, b. 1617 or 18.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1548_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209461</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90864)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 196:E1548[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spiritual flovvers for saints and sinners. Gathered out of the garden of the sacred scriptures, and writings of men famous in their generations. / By Robert Port minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Port, Robert, b. 1617 or 18.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 141, [3], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Dawson for George Sawbridge, at the sign of the Bible upon Ludgate-hill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An holy alphabet for young Christians" has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>SPIRITUAL FLOWERS FOR SAINTS AND SINNERS.</p>
                  <p>Gathered out of the Garden of the ſacred Scriptures, and Writings of Men famous in their Generations.</p>
                  <p>By ROBERT PORT Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Eccleſ. 12. ver. 11.</bibl> 
                     <hi>The words of the wiſe are as goades and nayles faſtned by the Maſters of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dawſon</hi> for <hi>George Sawbridge,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> upon <hi>Ludgate-hill.</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Courteous Reader.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Preſſe (I confeſs) is overpreſſed with ſome worthleſſe works (as I may call them) raw Eructa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of each petty Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and Readers are cloy'd and ſurfeited on variety in that kind. And Cenſure being ſo buſie
<pb facs="tcp:120685:3"/>
every where (blaſting hopeful labours in the very bud) might make me ſuſpect this of mine. Yet at an adventure (among ſuch a throng of Writers as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the world) I'le croud in for company.</p>
                  <p>This Book, thus compos'd and digeſted into heads, was intended to have attended my ſervice alone for ever, but that ſome worthy friends, whoſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious eye might becken me along to any good deſign, atteſted ſeriouſly, it would be very ſerviceable to Church and Common-wealth, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of holineſs. Whereupon I began to think with my ſelf (as the four Lepers, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7. 8, 9.) I ſhould not do well to hide or bury any thing, which might do others good, and
<pb facs="tcp:120685:3"/>
therefore I have now adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to publiſh it. Yet let it not render the modeſty of this Book ſuſpected, becauſe it preſumes to appear in company unmaned by any Patron: if right, it will defend it ſelf; if wrong, none can defend it.</p>
                  <p>And now I beſeech thee (as well by my Epiſtle, as by my Book) labour to keep cloſe to God in a looſe Age; ſpend not thy time in complaining of the licentiouſneſs of the time, in the mean time ſetting up a toleration in thine own heart and life.</p>
                  <p>Take heed in pleaſing thy ſelf in a bare formall profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; labour to be rooted in Chriſt, he who is but a viſible Chriſtian, may in a ſhort time ceaſe to be ſo much as viſible,
<pb facs="tcp:120685:4"/>
He who ſpeaks of Chriſt but notionally, may in time be won to ſpeak againſt him.</p>
                  <p>Lay the foundation of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication deep.</p>
                  <p>Love not the world.</p>
                  <p>Reſerve no luſt from the ſtroak of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Beware of ſcandals; take them not where they are; make them not, where they are not (the common ſin of our times, to black Religion and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and then to fear and hate both.)</p>
                  <p>Deſpiſe not the providences of God in the world; they are ſigns of Gods mind, though not of his love.</p>
                  <p>Delight in the publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and highly eſteem of faithful Miniſters; they and
<pb facs="tcp:120685:4"/>
Religion are commonly blaſted together.</p>
                  <p>Shun ſeducers; ſit down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Miniſter as well as under a Preacher.</p>
                  <p>He who will hear every one, may at length be brought to hear none, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 27.</p>
                  <p>And he who will hear him preach, who ought not, may ſoon be left to learn that which he ought not.</p>
                  <p>Preſerve a tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>Every ſtep thou takeſt fear a ſnare.</p>
                  <p>Read thine one heart in the wickedneſs of others.</p>
                  <p>Be not ſlight in Cloſet du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  <p>Oft think of God in thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Calling, for therein thou thinkeſt thou haſt leaſt leiſure,
<pb facs="tcp:120685:5"/>
but ſure thou haſt moſt need to do ſo.</p>
                  <p>In a word, I wiſh thee as much delight and benefit in the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of my Book, as it hath coſt me paines in collecting, digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tranſcribing and reviewing of it.</p>
                  <p>And as this ſhall find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with thee, I ſhall (as God ſhall give ſtrength and more leiſure) yet further approve my ſelf to be.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thy Servant in the Lord, to promots thy Faith and Comfort. R. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REader, be pleaſed to take notice, that the Author of theſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections (thus digeſted) is preparing for the Preſſe theſe Books following,</hi> viz.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. The holy Bible opened in ſeverall Sermons upon choice Texts, out of every Book in
<pb facs="tcp:120685:6"/>
the old and new Teſtament.</item>
                     <item>2 Light and Darkneſs, or Truth by Scripture plainly confirmed, and error confuted.</item>
                     <item>3 The Saints rich Cabinet opened and preſented to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view: Containing many choice and pretious Jewels, all which are reduced into Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall concluſions, Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally diſpoſed.</item>
                     <item>4 Phyſicall Gleanings, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally propounded.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:120685:6"/>5 Emmanuel or God with us, being an Annual Chronology from the year 1640. to 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> methodically compoſed.</item>
                     <item>6 The faithfull Shepheard guiding his flock to a conſtant walking with God.</item>
                     <item>7 Evangelicall Legacies for Saints and Sinners, tending to ſettle the wavering, to ſtay the wandering, and to ſtrengthen the fainting.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:7"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120685:7"/>
                  <head>Spiritual FLOWERS. For SAINTS and SINNERS.</head>
                  <div n="a" type="part">
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Admiring.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire nothing for, or in it ſelf; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire al things in God, and God in all things.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Action.</head>
                        <p>A good aime doth not make a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120685:8"/>
bad action good; but a bad aime makes a good action bad.</p>
                        <p>Many times there may be ſin in the action, when yet the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may not be ſin.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Actions.</head>
                        <p>A Chriſtian may uſually ſay, that all is not ill in his evil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor all good in his good actions.</p>
                        <p>Good actions (well done) better our ſelves, and benefit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Acknowledge.</head>
                        <p>It is good to acknowledge God to be juſt, and 'tis juſt to acknowledge God to be good in all his wayes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Adverſity.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to be preſerved in the brine of adverſity, then to rot in the honey of proſperity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:120685:8"/>
                        <head>Affections.</head>
                        <p>When our affections and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations are in heaven, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy heaven upon earth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Afflictions.</head>
                        <p>Afflictions are then a bleſſing to us, when we can bleſs God for afflictions.</p>
                        <p>Sanctified afflictions, as ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, croſſes and loſſes, are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than unſanctified health and gain.</p>
                        <p>Affliction ſeldome comes without being a temptation, but temptation never comes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being an affliction to the Saints.</p>
                        <p>Being afflicted doth often diſcover Hypocrites; yet being afflicted is no diſcovery of an Hypocrite.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Afflicted.</head>
                        <p>We are then truly afflicted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120685:9"/>
for ſin, when 'tis more for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing God, than for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God; more that he is diſpleaſed by us, than that he is diſpleaſed with us.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Alone.</head>
                        <p>Some men are leaſt alone, when moſt alone; when <hi>Jacob</hi> was left alone, he did wreſtle with God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>All in all.</head>
                        <p>It is for none but him who is all, and the fulneſs which filleth all in all, to give to all abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Angry.</head>
                        <p>The world is angry with Saints, that they are no worſe; and the Saints are angry with them and themſelves, that they are no better.</p>
                        <p>It doth not become us to be angry with God, though God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120685:9"/>
come to be angry with us.</p>
                        <p>He that is angry with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a cauſe, is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of judgement; and he is likewiſe in danger of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who is not angry with his Brother, when there is cauſe.</p>
                        <p>Anger can hardly be ſilent, but that anger is admirable, which ſpeaks and ſins not. Be angry, but ſin not.</p>
                        <p>He that will be angry for any thing, will be angry for nothing. <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> See <hi>Maen of Sin.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Appearance.</head>
                        <p>Appearance in good is too little, in evill 'tis too much.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Appearing.</head>
                        <p>They for whom, and to whom God appears much, ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear much for God.</p>
                        <p>Many men appear righteous, who are not righteous as they appear.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="6" facs="tcp:120685:10"/>
That which makes God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo glorious in our eyes, is his ſo gratious appearing, or appearing ſo gratious to the ſouls.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Apoſtles preaching.</head>
                        <p>The Apoſtles did preach to, and not lord it over the Lords inheritance; but ſince their dayes many lord it over, and few preach to the Lords inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Arguing.</head>
                        <p>The beſt arguments that we can uſe with Chriſt, are to tell him, that we, whom he loveth, are ſick, that we are ſick of love for him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Aſhamed.</head>
                        <p>Many men are aſhamed of that, wherein, or whereof, they ſhould glory, and glory in that whereof they ſhould be aſhamed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120685:10"/>
                        <head>Asking.</head>
                        <p>Though God hath promiſed to give to them that ask; yet many ask and miſs, becauſe they ask amiſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Aſſurance.</head>
                        <p>There may be grace where there is no aſſurance; but there can be no aſſurance where there is no grace.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="b" type="part">
                     <head>B</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Babes in Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>Babes in Chriſt are but as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men, yet are they not carnal as men that are but carnal; for ſuch are not babes, nor as babes in Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Baptized.</head>
                        <p>A man may be damned, though he be baptized, if he do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: and a man may be ſaved, if he do beleive, though he be not baptized.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:120685:11"/>
                        <head>Behaviour.</head>
                        <p>Its better to carry our ſelves ſo, that God may ſmile, and the world frown upon us; than to carry our ſelves ſo, as that the world ſhould ſmile, and God frown upon us.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould ſo behave himſelf, as not to be a ſhame to, nor aſhamed of the Goſpel.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Being in Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>'Tis one thing to profeſs and to beleive our ſelves to be in Chriſt; 'tis another thing to be in Chriſt, in whom we profeſs and beleive our ſelves to be: for many may beleive themſelves to be in Chriſt, who are not; and many may be in Chriſt, who do not beleive themſelves to be in Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Beleivers.</head>
                        <p>Believers are all for Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120685:11"/>
and Chriſt is all for Beleivers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Better than others.</head>
                        <p>When we ſee others better than our ſelves, we ſhould not grieve, but rejoyce, that they are better than our ſelves; yet we ſhould not rejoyce but greive, that we our ſelves are no better.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Beauty-Spots.</head>
                        <p>Chriſtians ſhould not went Beauty-ſpots (ſeeing beauty-ſpots are the ſpots of beauty) for their beauty is to be without ſpots.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Birth-day.</head>
                        <p>Some have curſed the day of their firſt birth, but never any curſed the day of their ſecond or new birth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Bleſſing God.</head>
                        <p>The tongue bleſſing God without the heart, is but a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Cymbal; the heart bleſſing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120685:12"/>
God without the tongue is ſweet, but ſtill muſick; both in conſort make their harmony, which fill and delights heaven and earth.</p>
                        <p>Seeing it pleaſeth the Lord to bleſs us, and that without cauſe given him, how much ſhould it pleaſe us to bleſs him, who hath given us ſo much cauſe to bleſs him.</p>
                        <p>God doth not onely bleſs his people when they turn away from every one of their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but God doth alſo bleſſe them in turning away every one of them from their iniquity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-bleſſings.</head>
                        <p>When we begin to bleſſe our ſelves in earthly enjoyments, God blaſteth them to us, either in taking them from us, or us from them: or if he leaves us
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120685:12"/>
the things, he takes away the comfort of them.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Blood of Chriſt and Saints.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The bloud of Saints is preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of Chriſt, and the bloud of Chriſt is pretious in the ſight of the Saints.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Bluſhing.</head>
                        <p>Some men bluſh to be known to be wicked, who bluſh not to be wicked, though it be known.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Body of Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>The body of the Lord was dead and buried, but not the Lord of the body.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="c" type="part">
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Calling.</head>
                        <p>Every man ſhould have a Calling to follow, and follow his Calling.</p>
                        <p>Every man ſhould ſerve God in his vocation, and ſome, whoſe vocation it ſhould be to ſerve God; as all ſhould do it, ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120685:13"/>
ſome ſhould doe nothing elſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Called.</head>
                        <p>The Apoſtle, though he ſaith, not many, yet he doth not ſay, not any rich are called; thus, that none might deſpair. Though he doth not ſay, not any rich, yet he doth ſay, not many rich are called; thus, that none might preſume.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Saints Care.</head>
                        <p>A Saint cares to keep himſelf in Gods way, yet leaves the care of himſelf, and his way, to God.</p>
                        <p>Men cannot enter into the cares of the world, but they muſt enter into a world of cares.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Carnal men.</head>
                        <p>Carnal men love the God that they make, and hate the God that made them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Children.</head>
                        <p>Stones cannot make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120685:13"/>
the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but God can make ſtones the Children of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A Child of light may for a time walk in darkneſs, and for a time a Child of darkneſs may walk in light.</p>
                        <p>'Tis one thing to be a Child under wrath, another thing to be a Child of wrath.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>Chriſt is the Chriſtians patron, and the Chriſtians patern.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt was made like to us, that he might be tempted; and we are tempted, that we might be made like to Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt, who did our work for us without us, will alſo work his work for us within us.</p>
                        <p>They who make a prey of them that are Chriſts, ſhall themſelves become a prey unto Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="14" facs="tcp:120685:14"/>
Chriſt by drawing neer unto the Saints, draws them neer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf.</p>
                        <p>A gratious ſoul ſo longs to be with Chriſt, that he thinks it long ere he be diſſolved, that he might go to his long (his long'd for) home.</p>
                        <p>All the while Chriſt is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, we are without Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>The worſt of Chriſt is better than the beſt of the world; the afflictions of Chriſt better than the pleaſures of ſin, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of Chriſt, greater rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es than the treaſures of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It was Chriſts abaſement to be like us; but 'tis our advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be like Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Chriſts work.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to have the work of Chriſt in our hearts, than the perſon of Chriſt in our houſes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:120685:14"/>
Chriſt died that ſinners might live.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Chriſt perſecuted.</head>
                        <p>Chriſt was firſt perſecuted by <hi>Paul</hi> in his members, and was afterwards perſecuted in <hi>Paul,</hi> one of his members.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Chriſt our Mine.</head>
                        <p>'Tis more worth than all the mines of the world, to be able to ſay, Chriſt is mine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Chriſtian.</head>
                        <p>One may be an honeſt man (as they ſay) and pay every man his due, &amp;c. and yet not be a Chriſtian; but one cannot be a Chriſtian, and not be an honeſt man, and pay every man his due, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>A man ſhould not be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian onely in ſhew; yet in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing a man ſhould ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Chriſtian.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:120685:15"/>
                        <head>Almoſt a Chriſtian.</head>
                        <p>Moſt of the all that profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, are ('tis to be feared) but almoſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
                        <p>He that's but almoſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, will be but almoſt ſaved, that is, may go from the gates of heaven to the belly of hell; though he be not far from the kingdom of heaven, yet the kingdom of heaven is far from him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Civility.</head>
                        <p>Civility and morality without ſanctity, is but guilded infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Comfort.</head>
                        <p>A Saint had rather have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs without comfort, than comfort without holineſs.</p>
                        <p>The Saints have more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from Gods love to them,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120685:15"/>
than they have from their love to God.</p>
                        <p>'Tis better to enjoy ſoul-comforts, though one have none for the body, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy bodily comforts, and have none for the ſoul.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jobs</hi> friends could do no leſs than come to comfort him, yet when they came, they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than comfort him.</p>
                        <p>'Tis very rare that God takes outward comforts from them, who are not taken with their comfort; but if he take them, that ſhall be their Comfort.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Company.</head>
                        <p>Many are pleaſed with the company of them, who are good, that are not pleaſed with the good of the company.</p>
                        <p>'Tis to be feared, that they that love wicked men, doe not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120685:16"/>
hate the wickedneſs of men: or,</p>
                        <p>That they that love the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the wicked, do not hate the wickedneſs of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
                        <p>He that loves ill company, will learn it, if not the ill of the company.</p>
                        <p>No man ſhould do ill for company, nor good onely for company.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Communion.</head>
                        <p>Communion with God, is more in converſation with God, than in contemplation with God.</p>
                        <p>That God might have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us, Chriſt was made partaker of the humane nature; and that we might have communion with God, we are made partakers of the divine nature.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:120685:16"/>
                        <head>Complement.</head>
                        <p>Compleat ſpeech is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, if men ſpeak as they intend, and intend as they ſpeak.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Complaint.</head>
                        <p>Saints have not ſuch often occaſion to complain, that what they have done is ill, as that what they have done is ill done.</p>
                        <p>Many complain of their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings without a cauſe, wherein they ſhould rather rejoyce; for 'tis better to ſuffer without a cauſe, than that there ſhould be a cauſe for our ſufferings.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Confuſion.</head>
                        <p>That which is confuſion to us, is no confuſion to God; for God hath the ordering of, and an order in all confuſion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Commandements.</head>
                        <p>All Gods Commandements are alike (holy, juſt and good)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120685:17"/>
and therefore we ſhould like them all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Condemnation.</head>
                        <p>If that ſervant was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that gave God his own, what will become of them that rob God of his own.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Conſcience.</head>
                        <p>A good conſcience without a good name, is better than a good name without a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
                        <p>A Saint will hazard his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to ſave his conſcience, rather than hazard his conſcience to ſave his credit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Contentation.</head>
                        <p>We ſhould be ſo content with every condition, as to think the preſent beſt, yet many times it's beſt to think it ſo but for the preſent.</p>
                        <p>Contentment without the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120685:17"/>
world, is better than the world without contentment.</p>
                        <p>The loweſt condition in the world, with the love of God, is better than the higheſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, without the love of God.</p>
                        <p>A Saint is content, not onely that the will of the Lord ſhould be done, but that it ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo done to Gods content.</p>
                        <p>How little ſoever we injoy, there is great reaſon we ſhould be contented, and how much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſoever we undergo, there's no reaſon we ſhould be diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Converſion.</head>
                        <p>Before converſion men are willingly willing to ſin, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter converſion men are willingly unwilling to ſin.</p>
                        <p>There are many convictions without converſion, but there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120685:18"/>
no converſion without convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
                        <p>Before converſion ſin hath dominion over us; but after converſion we have dominion over ſin, and we lead that into captivity, which did before lead us captives.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Covetous.</head>
                        <p>Uſually covetous men need money leaſt, yet moſt affect it, and prodigals, who need it moſt, do leaſt regard it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Covenant.</head>
                        <p>The tie of the Covenant is ſure, for Chriſt is the ſurety of the Covenant.</p>
                        <p>In the Covenant of works, God did firſt accept of the works, and then of the perſon; but in the Covenant of grace, God doth firſt accept the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then the work.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:120685:18"/>
                        <head>Contradictions.</head>
                        <p>It ſeems to many, that there are contradictions in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but they are not, but ſo many ſeeming contradictions.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Creation.</head>
                        <p>In creation God gave us to our ſelves, but in redemption he gave himſelf to us.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Creature-Comforts.</head>
                        <p>When we take comfort in Creatures without God, he takes away the Creatures, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Croſſe.</head>
                        <p>Chriſt did bear the curſe, and therefore 'tis but reaſon that we ſhould bear the croſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Croſſes.</hi> See <hi>Afflictions.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Changes of conditions are but exchanges of mercy to a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſoul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Crucified.</head>
                        <p>If we be not crucified with Chriſt, Chriſt being crucified
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120685:19"/>
will not deliver us from death, for we may die in our ſins, and be damned notwithſtandihg, if we do not riſe with Chriſt, Chriſts reſurrection will not ſave us; it is not Chriſt without us, but Chriſt within us, who is our hope of glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 27.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="d" type="part">
                     <head>D</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Death.</head>
                        <p>That man can never die an evill death (at leaſt no kind of death can be evill to that man) who hath lead a good life.</p>
                        <p>Death comes in by ſin, and ſin goeth out by death.</p>
                        <p>The death of the body frees us from the body of death.</p>
                        <p>Death hath nothing terrible in it, but what our life hath made ſo.</p>
                        <p>When Saints die, they leave all their bad behind, and carry all their good with them; but when a Sinner dieth, he leaves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120685:19"/>
all his good, &amp; carries all his bad: the one goes from evil to good, the other from good to evill.</p>
                        <p>Our ſin delivered Chriſt to death, and Chriſt's death deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers us from our ſin.</p>
                        <p>Its appointed for all men once to die, and to ſome men its appointed to die but once; the reſt ſhall have their ſhare in a ſecond death, wherein they ſhall find no reſt.</p>
                        <p>The natural death is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the ſoul from the body; the ſpiritual death is the ſeparation of the ſoul from God; and the eternal death is, the eternal ſeparation of the ſoul and body from God.</p>
                        <p>Think of death, as a thing thou muſt meet with, and of life, as a thing thou muſt part with; and therefore not to love that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120685:20"/>
life too well, that keeps thee (if a Saint) from a better, nor at all to fear that death, that leads thee to a better life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deeds.</head>
                        <p>That deed is ill done, wherein God is no ſharer.</p>
                        <p>No evill action can be well done; but a good action may be ill done.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Debts paying.</head>
                        <p>While we are paying Gods due debts, we make our ſelves the more his debtors; Lord, let me be thus in debt.</p>
                        <p>The more we pay God, the more we owe him, ſeeing we give nothing to him; but what he firſt gives to us.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Laſt Dayes.</head>
                        <p>A Chriſtians laſt dayes ſhould be his beſt dayes, and his fruits at laſt more than at firſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:120685:20"/>
                        <head>Defie, Deifie.</head>
                        <p>Many defie the devil, ſin and the world with their mouthes, but deifie them in their lives.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Die.</head>
                        <p>He that's fitteſt to die is fitteſt to live; and he that's fitteſt to live is fitteſt to die.</p>
                        <p>When a Saint comes to die, his greateſt grief is, that he hath done no more for God, and his greateſt joy is, that God hath done ſo much for him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Dead-living.</head>
                        <p>Some are alive and dead at the ſame time, for they that live in ſin, and the pleaſures of ſin, are dead while they live.</p>
                        <p>Saints are living dead men, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 19. 20. and ſinners are dead living men, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1, 2. yea, they are both dead and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, alive and dead at the ſame time.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:120685:21"/>
                        <head>Delayes, Denials.</head>
                        <p>Delayes are not denials, and denials are not alwayes refuſals of prayer. Sometimes Gods no, is no negative, God may delay long, and deny often, yet grant at laſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deliverance.</head>
                        <p>Many injoy deliverance from God, who yet do not injoy God in the deliverance.</p>
                        <p>Men are ſometimes delivered up to Satan, that they may be delivered from Satan, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-Denial.</head>
                        <p>A Saint ſhould ſo deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as to be nothing at all, that Chriſt might be all in all.</p>
                        <p>They that deny not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their own ends for Chriſt, will deny Chriſt for their own ends; and will (wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120685:21"/>
them) themſelves be denied by Chriſt in the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deceiving.</head>
                        <p>They that think (as all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites do) to deceive God, will find that they deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deſert.</head>
                        <p>He that deſerves nothing, ſhould be content with any thing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deſire.</head>
                        <p>They can never want much, who deſire but a little, nor they ever have enough, whoſe deſires are unbounded.</p>
                        <p>There will be no end of deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, till we deſire that which hath no end.</p>
                        <p>Leſſe than one of theſe two deſires granted, either that he may be with God in heaven, or that God will be with him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120685:22"/>
on earth, will not ſatisfie a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deſpair.</head>
                        <p>None ſhould deſpair, becauſe God can help them; and none ſhould preſume, becauſe God can croſs them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Deſtruction.</head>
                        <p>It uſually falls out, that they who ſeek others deſtruction, find their own.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Diligent.</head>
                        <p>A diligent hand cannot make rich without God; and God doth ſeldome make rich without a diligent hand.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Diſputing.</head>
                        <p>The great end of diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould be either to convince others, or to be convinced by others of the truth.</p>
                        <p>Many men, while they ſpend their time in diſputing what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120685:22"/>
they ſhould do, do (too too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) neglect to do the things which are without diſpute.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Doctrine and Life.</head>
                        <p>When there is no Doctrine in the Life, there is but little life in the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Doing.</head>
                        <p>Let Chriſtians do their beſt, and then let the world do their worſt.</p>
                        <p>That cannot be done too ſoon, which ſhould be alwayes a doing, as ſerving of God; yet better doing late than never, for 'tis never too late.</p>
                        <p>Moſt mens doings turn moſt to their undoing.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould do no more than he may lawfully do, and he ſhould not do all that he may do lawfully.</p>
                        <p>Some men undo themſelves
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120685:23"/>
by doing, and ſome are made by being undone.</p>
                        <p>A man may do the things which pleaſe God, and yet not pleaſe God in doing the things.</p>
                        <p>He that will forbear at no time to do ſomething, which he may lawfully do, will ('tis ten to one) at ſome time or other do ſomething, which he may not lawfully do.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian loves God, and fears God; he fears to do any thing againſt him, becauſe he loves him; and he loves not to do any thing againſt him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he fears him.</p>
                        <p>Rather fear to do ill, than to ſuffer for thy ill doing.</p>
                        <p>There is little difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween not doing what thou ſhouldeſt, and not doing it as thou ſhouldeſt; for to do thy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120685:23"/>
duty onely in ſhew, or onely for a ſhew, is to do thy duty, and be ſtill undutiful.</p>
                        <p>To diſlike what God doth, is to do what God diſlikes. A double ball.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to which he would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly deſire Gods abſence, or upon which he may not ask a bleſſing and aſſiſtance from God, nor as neer (as he can) any thing, for which he ſhould need to ask his pardon.</p>
                        <p>A man ſhould do nothing, which ſhould not be imitated, and a man ſhould imitate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which ſhould not be done.</p>
                        <p>If that which thou doſt be right, and the mind with which thou doſt it be not ſo, all is wrong, and a man forfeits the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120685:24"/>
acceptation of what was good, by the ill performance.</p>
                        <p>Be careful to do nothing that deſerves to be ill ſpoken of, and then thou needeſt not care if thou be undeſervedly ſpoken ill of.</p>
                        <p>'Tis the height of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to do ill, and think it well done.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Drunkenneſs,</head>
                        <p>When men are drunk with wine, wherein there is exceſs, the wine doth not ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the men, as the men do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the wine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Duties.</head>
                        <p>Priviledges annexed to any duties or graces, are made good by God when the graces are acted, and the duties performed by us; ſo that God is not behind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with us in performance of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120685:24"/>
promiſes, if we be not behind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with God in performance of duties.</p>
                        <p>Free-grace calls for full du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                        <p>Duties done for God, are no hinderance to duties to be done to God.</p>
                        <p>All the duty of men, the duty of all men is compriſed in this, <hi>Fear God and keep his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> for this is the whole of men, this is a mans all, the reſt being but vanity and vexation of Spirit.</p>
                        <p>Many men pleaſe themſelves in the duties they have done, though in doing of them they have not pleaſed God, but we ſhould not take content in any duty, wherein we do not give God content.</p>
                        <p>They that are moſt full of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120685:25"/>
are not alwayes moſt duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
                        <p>We ſhould be willing to be like them (on earth) in duty, whom we would be like (in heaven) in glory; if <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s boſom be deſirable, why ſhould not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s faith and obedience? ſeeing, unleſs we be faithful (though not ſo full of faith) as <hi>Abraham,</hi> we are not like to be glorified as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="e" type="part">
                     <head>E</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Earthly things.</head>
                        <p>Earthly things are ſuch as the worſt of men may have, and the beſt of men may be without; yet he that hath them not, may be happy without them, and he that hath them, may be miſerable with them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:120685:25"/>
                        <head>Election, Calling.</head>
                        <p>Our Calling is the firſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of our ſecret election, and a fore-runner of our glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and is the very voice of God, fore-telling us that he will ſave us.</p>
                        <p>Our election doth not depend upon our faith, but faith depends upon election; nor juſtification upon works, but works upon ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</p>
                        <p>We are not elected becauſe we are holy, but we are elected that we may be holy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Enjoyment of God.</head>
                        <p>The enjoyment of God is the joy of our life, and the life of our joy, whatever our fare be, that alone is our chear; how well ſoever we fare, that alone is our welfare.</p>
                        <p>Some men have not leiſure to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120685:26"/>
enjoy what they have (yea, they forget what they have) for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of more.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Enjoyning.</head>
                        <p>They that forbid what God enjoynes, and they that enjoyn what God forbids, are both an abomination.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Error.</head>
                        <p>There is a great deal of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt an error of love, and the love of an error.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Eſtates.</head>
                        <p>If we cannot raiſe our eſtates to our mind, we ſhould ſtoop our minds to our eſtates.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Evill good.</head>
                        <p>Evill things work together for good to them that love God, but good things work together for evill to them that hate God.</p>
                        <p>Though a man ſhould take
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120685:26"/>
more care, not to be evill, than not to appear to be ſo; yet he ſhould take care to abſtain from appearing, and from the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of evil.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Exalting.</head>
                        <p>God exalts ſome men to caſt them down, and God caſts ſome men down to exalt them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Excellency.</head>
                        <p>'Tis not excellency in any man to be ignorant of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; but this is a mans excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that though he know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo, yet he is not proud of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ions.</head>
                        <p>'Tis a wonder to ſee how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny exceptions the Chriſtian makes againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>imſelf, and how few exceptions God makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtian.</p>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:120685:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:120685:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="40" facs="tcp:120685:28"/>
A man ſhould not willingly give, nor eaſily take excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="f" type="part">
                     <head>F</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Faith.</head>
                        <p>'Tis not the work Faith, nor the work of Faith, but a working Faith, or rather he who works faith, by which we are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                        <p>As without faith 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for works to pleaſe God; ſo 'tis impoſſible for faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works to pleaſe God.</p>
                        <p>There are many poor in this world rich in faith, and many rich in this world poor in faith.</p>
                        <p>Faith gets moſt, humility keeps moſt, and love doth moſt. The more full of faith, and the more painful men are, the more they pleaſe God.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="41" facs="tcp:120685:28"/>
Though <hi>Abraham</hi>'s faith were not a faith of miracles, yet it was the more miraculous, for it was a miracle of faith.</p>
                        <p>Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not ſeen.</p>
                        <p>Many mens faith is but fancy, and many men will fancy their faith to be but ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Faith glorified.</head>
                        <p>God hath in this world glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified faith moſt, above all other graces; and above all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces faith glorifies God moſt in this world.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Faithfulneſs.</head>
                        <p>Though our faithfulneſs to God doth often fail, yet Gods faithfulneſs to us doth never fail.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Faults finding:</head>
                        <p>We ſhould take care, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120685:29"/>
that which we find fault with in others, ſhould not in others be found to be our fault.</p>
                        <p>Some men will be finding fault, when and where there's no fault to be found.</p>
                        <p>The reaſon why Chriſtians do find ſo much fault with themſelves is, becauſe they find themſelves ſo much in fault, or becauſe they find ſo many faults within themſelves.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Fleſh, Spirit.</head>
                        <p>Though the Saints live in the fleſh, yet they are not fleſh; for that which is born (as the Saint is) of the Spirit, is Spirit, and walketh in the Spirit.</p>
                        <p>As it ſads the Saints to find the fleſh luſting againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the law of the members warring againſt the law of the mind; ſo it glads him to find
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120685:29"/>
the Spirit luſting againſt the fleſh, and the law of his mind warring againſt the law of his members.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Failing Falling.</head>
                        <p>Saints may fail and fall in the way; but Saints cannot fall away.</p>
                        <p>Though Saints are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from failing, no nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together from falling, yet they are preſerved from falling alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. They may part with Chriſt for a time, but ſhall not depart from Chriſt for ever.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Fool.</head>
                        <p>He is not ſo much a fool, who hath no wit to uſe, as he that doth not uſe the wit he hath, or he that abuſeth it by playing the fool in wit.</p>
                        <p>A fool ſpeaks with an open mouth, but a wiſe man open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120685:30"/>
his mouth and ſpeakes,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Forgiveneſs.</head>
                        <p>God promiſeth forgiveneſs of ſins to all that repent; but God doth not promiſe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to all or any that ſin.</p>
                        <p>Its a greater vertue to forgive one injury, than to do many cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies, becauſe its harder and harder, becauſe more againſt nature, for many a man will do for another, that will not ſuffer for him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Fear God.</head>
                        <p>To fear God and keep his Commandement is all that we have to do, and that we all have to do.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Freinds.</head>
                        <p>He is happy that finds a true friend in extremity, but he is happier, that knows no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity wherein to try his friend</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:120685:30"/>
Though we prize our freinds much, we ſhould praiſe them but little, and to their faces not at all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Find.</hi> See <hi>Heaven. Following God.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Many men follow God for the worlds ſake, but few men follow the world for Gods ſake.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Food.</head>
                        <p>Man turns natural food into his nature, but ſpiritual food turns man into its nature.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Fortunes.</head>
                        <p>High fortunes are the way to high minds, and high minds are the high-way to great fortunes, for pride goeth before, but not far before a fall.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Freedom by Chriſt,</head>
                        <p>Jeſus Chriſt hath delivered us from this preſent evill world,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120685:31"/>
though we are not at preſent delivered from the evill of this world.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Friendſhip.</head>
                        <p>That freindſhip will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to the end, which is begun for an end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Fulneſs.</head>
                        <p>The wicked in the fulneſs of their ſufficiency are in ſtraits; but the godly in the fulneſs of their ſtraits have a ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="g" type="part">
                     <head>G</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Getting Gain.</head>
                        <p>All that a man gets is not gain, few men get profit by their getting; they will have but a bad bargain, that get the world, and looſe their ſouls.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gain, Loſs.</head>
                        <p>Men gain moſt by looſing, and they looſe moſt by gaining, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 25.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:120685:31"/>
                        <head>Gifts.</head>
                        <p>All the gifts and graces which God laies in our ſouls, ſhould not be laid up as in a napkin, but laid out for Gods glory and others good.</p>
                        <p>Hypocrites are apt to think, that they have grace, becauſe they have gifts; and Saints are many times thinking, that they have no grace, becauſe they have no gifts.</p>
                        <p>No gift coming from God is ſo mean, as to be deſpiſed, nor is there any ſo great as to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>God good.</head>
                        <p>God is good to us when he ſends us evill, becauſe he ſends us evil for our good.</p>
                        <p>If God be good to them that ſeek him, what is he then to them that find him? Oh how good!</p>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:120685:32"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:120685:32"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="48" facs="tcp:120685:33"/>
God may as ſoon ceaſe to be God, as ceaſe to be good; as ſoon ceaſe to live, as ceaſe to love.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gods indearing.</head>
                        <p>This indears God to a Saint, and makes him pretious in his eyes, that he is ſo dear and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the eyes of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>God lovely.</head>
                        <p>God is lovely in all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, more lovely in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but moſt of all lovely in Chriſt, who is altogether love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not mans lovelineſs, but Gods lovingneſs, that engageth God to love and ſave him.</p>
                        <p>God loves his people when he ſtrikes them, as well as when he ſtroaks them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>God reſting.</head>
                        <p>God reſted not till he had
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120685:33"/>
made man like himſelf, and man ſhould not reſt till he be made like God, or partaker of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>God giving.</head>
                        <p>God is a giving and a forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, an open-handed and open-hearted God: open-handed in giving to us, and open-hearted in forgiving of us.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gods putting down.</head>
                        <p>God uſually puts down that which man exalts, becauſe what man exalts doth uſually tend to the putting down of God.</p>
                        <p>All the world cannot put down an humble man, becauſe God will exalt him, and all the world cannot exalt a proud man, becauſe God will pull him down.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Men, Gods.</head>
                        <p>The Heathen made Gods of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120685:34"/>
men, and men of their Gods; attributing divine vertues to men, and humane vices to their Gods.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Good.</head>
                        <p>He that thinks he was ever good, was never good.</p>
                        <p>He was never ſo good as he ſhould be, that doth not ſtrive to be better than he is.</p>
                        <p>Its a good proof that a man is good, when he labours to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himſelf good to God and to men, and yet approves of himſelf more according to Gods approbation, than mans appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of him.</p>
                        <p>As we muſt not attribute to God the ill that proceeds from man, ſo we muſt not attribute to man the good which proceeds from God.</p>
                        <p>Some men are unwillingly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120685:34"/>
willing to do good, thats's bad; others are willingly unwilling to do good, that's worſt; but ſome are willingly willing, and that's beſt.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not ſo much a mercy to have wherewithall to do good, as to do good with what we have.</p>
                        <p>No man but he hath received more good than he hath done, and hath done more evill than he hath firſt ſuffered; and therefore ſhould be content, though he receive but little good, and not diſcontent, though he ſuffer much evill.</p>
                        <p>The good which we receive is not for our own ſake<hi>:</hi> and the good which we do is not by our own power, its the mercy of God that moves him to do any thing for us, and that enables
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120685:35"/>
us to do any thing for him.</p>
                        <p>A man ſhould not omit good when he hath, nor commit evil, though he have an opportunity to do it.</p>
                        <p>Inward goodneſs, without an outward ſhew of it, is like a tree without fruit, uſeleſs. And out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhews of goodneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inward ſincerity, is like a tree without heart, liveleſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Goods.</head>
                        <p>Wicked men have their goods from the will of God; but the Saints have theirs from the good will of God.</p>
                        <p>Men are not more happy in having more goods, but in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more good than other men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Godlineſs a Myſtery.</head>
                        <p>Though the myſtery of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs be not without great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120685:35"/>
yet great without controverſie is the myſtery of godlineſs.</p>
                        <p>Men that reſolve to make gain their godlineſs, will never gain godlineſs, unleſs they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve counter, to make godlineſs their gain.</p>
                        <p>Some men, inſtead of making godlineſs their greateſt pleaſure and gain, make gain and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their greateſt godlineſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gold a vanity.</head>
                        <p>Gold is a ſolid, well compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and weighty metall: and yet gold (not onely leaf gold, or light gold, but gold) that's weighty is lighter than vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Glory.</head>
                        <p>In this life the glory of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is but revealed to us, but in the life to come it ſhall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120685:36"/>
be revealed in us.</p>
                        <p>The glory of all our hereafter glory, will be an oneneſs of communion with the Father, Son and Spirit, Angels and one another in God, who is one in all, and all in one.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Glorifie.</head>
                        <p>We cannot be ſaid to glorifie God, though we do the things that glorifie him, unleſs we do the things to glorifie him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Goſpel.</head>
                        <p>The Goſpel diſcovers a juſt God to be a friend to unjuſt man, without being unjuſt either to himſelf or man.</p>
                        <p>The Goſpel of peace is a great bleſſing, but the peace of the Goſpel is a greater bleſſing.</p>
                        <p>The Goſpel breaks hard hearts, and heals broken hearts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:120685:36"/>
                        <head>Grace.</head>
                        <p>One grain of grace is more worth than many pounds of gifts, or a gift of many pounds.</p>
                        <p>Grace makes a man more a man, and more than a man.</p>
                        <p>Grace is glory begun, and glory is grace made perfect.</p>
                        <p>Seeing God will turn grace into our glory hereafter, we ſhould turn grace into his glory here.</p>
                        <p>The motions of grace are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly more excellent than the notions of grace.</p>
                        <p>That can never be a grace to the body, which is a diſgrace to the ſoul.</p>
                        <p>There are promiſes of grace, and there are promiſes to grace. The promiſes of grace are made good by working the grace of the promiſe in the ſoul: But the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120685:37"/>
promiſes to grace are not made good till the grace (to which the promiſe is made) be acted by the ſoul.</p>
                        <p>Grace out-works, and works out, ſin in Saints.</p>
                        <p>Grace is the beſt wear, for it wears not out in wearing, all other things periſh in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
                        <p>The God of all grace, and all the grace of God, is engaged to keep the Saints to eternal life.</p>
                        <p>We may well wait for the Lords grace, ſeeing the Lord waits to be gratious.</p>
                        <p>'Tis one thing to be wanting in grace, 'tis another thing to want grace.</p>
                        <p>All Saints have all grace in ſome degree, but few have all grace in an high degree.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="57" facs="tcp:120685:37"/>
Going on in grace, is a kind of growing in grace; for grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in grace is not ſo much a new thing, as the ſame thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed; 'tis acting the ſame gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces over and over, and better and better. Abounding is grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in grace.</p>
                        <p>What could God do more for us than accept us of his grace<hi>:</hi> and what leſs could God require of us, than to accept of his grace?</p>
                        <p>Men may ſpeak of grace unto us, but God onely can ſpeak grace into us.</p>
                        <p>Saving grace is everlaſting grace.</p>
                        <p>A Saint feels the grace which he cannot expreſs, an Hypocrite expreſſeth the grace which he doth not feel.</p>
                        <p>The meanes of grace is but a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:120685:38"/>
mean thing if compar'd with grace, which is the main thing.</p>
                        <p>There may be an omiſſion, but never an amiſſion of grace.</p>
                        <p>A Saint doth not deſire grace, onely that he may be glorified, but that he may glorifie God: not onely that he may be ſaved, but that he may be ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Greatneſs and goodneſs.</head>
                        <p>Goodneſs without greatneſs, is better than greatnsſs without goodneſs.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not mans goodneſs, but Gods goodneſs, which makes a difference betwixt man and man.</p>
                        <p>To be very great and very good, is a very great good.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="h" type="part">
                     <head>H</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Heart.</head>
                        <p>A thankful heart for all Gods
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120685:38"/>
bleſſings, is the greateſt of all bleſſings,</p>
                        <p>That mans heart can be but ſeldome pure, whoſe tongue is often impure, for out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</p>
                        <p>Some men ſet their hearts on that, on which God would that they ſet onely their feet, <hi>viz.</hi> the earth.</p>
                        <p>We have (alas!) but too often our hearts to ſeek, when we come to ſeek God, whom we ſhould ſeek and ſerve with all our hearts.</p>
                        <p>When the heart is upright with God, he accounts all as well done, as if all were not well done, yea, he looks on that as done, which was never done.</p>
                        <p>The hearts of Saints are larger than their words, but the words
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120685:39"/>
of Hypocrites are larger than their hands,</p>
                        <p>God brings his people into various conditions, that they may know what is in their hearts towards him, and what is in his heart towards them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Worldly Happineſs.</head>
                        <p>Corn, and Wine, and Oyle, is the worldlings happineſs, and but a worldly happineſs, for when the world is at an end, happineſs it at an end with them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Hatred, Love.</head>
                        <p>The Devil doth not, nay, the Devil cannot hate a Saint ſo much as God loves a Saint.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Heaven.</head>
                        <p>While the Saints are on earth, Chriſt is preparing heaven for them, and them for heaven.</p>
                        <p>If we doe not find that in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120685:39"/>
heaven which we did imagine, yet we ſhall find more than we did imagine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Helping-hand.</head>
                        <p>It many times falls out, that that hand is fartheſt off from helping, that is neereſt at hand to help the helpleſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Holy.</head>
                        <p>Saints ſtrive to be holy, as God is holy, they know they cannot be as holy as God is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Holineſs.</head>
                        <p>Our holineſs cauſeth not Gods love, but Gods love cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our love.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould not onely be perfecting holineſs, but we ſhould alſo be perfect in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                        <p>He that loves not holineſs in the ſeed time of his life, cannot
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120685:40"/>
expect to reap happineſs in the harveſt of eternity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Hope, Patience.</head>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould poſſeſs his ſoul in the patience of hope, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his ſoul poſſeſs that which he hath patiently hoped for.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Honour.</head>
                        <p>To deſerve honour and not to have it, is better than to have honour and not deſerve it.</p>
                        <p>None honour God ſo much, and God honours none ſo much, as the humble ſouls.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Humbled ones.</head>
                        <p>There are many humbled ones, that are not humble ones.</p>
                        <p>He that humbleth himſelf ſhall be exalted, but he that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelf ſhall be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:120685:40"/>
                        <head>Hypocrites, Saints.</head>
                        <p>The great difference between Saints and Hypocrites is this, that the Hypocrite hath but the expreſſion of grace, the Saint the experience of it; the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite hath the notion, the Saint the motion; the one reads, hears, and ſpeaks of it, the other ſees, taſts, and feels it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="i" type="part">
                     <head>I</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Idle.</head>
                        <p>Its as great fault to be idle, as to work on a Sabbath day.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Jeſt, Earneſt.</head>
                        <p>As a man ſhould not conſtrue that in earneſt which is ſpoken but in jeſt, ſo a man ſhould not ſpeak that in jeſt, which may be conſtrued in earneſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Innocency.</head>
                        <p>Good meaning and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:120685:41"/>
are careleſs, and ſeldome fore-think what anſwer to make to their accuſers, whence Chriſt ſaid, take no thought, what or how you ſhall ſpeak.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Intention.</head>
                        <p>Not to intend what thou ſpeakeſt, is to give thy heart the lie with thy tongue; not to perform what thou promiſeth, is to give thy tongue the lie with thine actions.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-Intereſt.</head>
                        <p>Self-intereſt carried on by policy, puts many civil men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to civill (or rather uncivil) war.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>Jeſus Chriſt is not the Son of God, becauſe he is the Meſſiah, but he is the Meſſiah, becauſe he is the Son of God.</p>
                        <p>Jeſus Chriſt loſt his own life,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120685:41"/>
that he might ſave the life of his own. Though it grieves a poor ſoul, that Chriſt was peirced by him, yet it releives a poor ſoul, that Chriſt was peirced for him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Joy.</head>
                        <p>The joy of the holy Ghoſt is ſuch as that there is both want in words, and want of words to expreſs it; for 'tis joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and full of glory.</p>
                        <p>Our Maſters joy enters into us here, and we ſhall enter into our Maſters joy hereafter.</p>
                        <p>'Tis the Saints greateſt joy to enjoy God, and to joy in God.</p>
                        <p>Joy is as troubleſome in the time of ſorrow, as ſorrow is in the time of joy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Iſraels God.</head>
                        <p>The God of Iſrael will doe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120685:42"/>
them good, that do good to the Iſrael of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Judging.</head>
                        <p>Men judge of our hearts by our words and works, but God judgeth of our words and works by our hearts.</p>
                        <p>Some mens judgements re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide more in their wills, than their wills do in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Juſtified.</head>
                        <p>We are not juſtified by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in Chriſt, but by Chriſt beleived in us; as a man is not healed by the applying of a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but by the plaiſter applied<hi>:</hi> faith is not our righteouſneſs, for our righteouſneſs is by faith.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="k" type="part">
                     <head>K</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Kingdom.</head>
                        <p>The propheſies concerning
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120685:42"/>
Chriſts kingdom, will not be compleatly fulfilled, till Chriſts kingdom be fully compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                        <p>A godly man is as willing that the kingdom of God ſhall come into him, as he is willing to goe into the kingdome of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>God knowing.</head>
                        <p>God doth know not onely the meaning (the ſenſe) of the words which man ſpeaks; but he alſo knows the meaning (the aim, the ſcope, and the end) of the man that ſpeaks the word.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Knowledge.</head>
                        <p>Knowledge may be without grace, but grace cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge.</p>
                        <p>'Tis better to have knowledge formed in one, than to have a form of knowledge.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="68" facs="tcp:120685:43"/>
Knowledge helps much to practiſe, and practiſe helps much to knowledge, for if any man do my will, he ſhall know the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine whether it be of God.</p>
                        <p>We may ſometimes know that by others, which we would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver care to utter; but we ſhould ever take care how (if ever) we utter that which we do not know.</p>
                        <p>The moſt perfect knowledge that we have of God, is that we cannot, or do not know him perfectly.</p>
                        <p>'Tis one thing to know Chriſt by a relation made of him to us, another thing to know Chriſt by a revelation made of him within us.</p>
                        <p>He that knows not God, knows nothing.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="l" type="part">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:120685:43"/>
                     <head>L</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Laity and Clergy.</head>
                        <p>Among them that are called the Laity you may find many children of light; and among them that are called the Clergy, you may find many children of darkneſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Laugh.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better that men ſhould laugh at us for being godly, than that God ſhould laugh at us for being ungodly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Leaſt, moſt.</head>
                        <p>Men are then leaſt in their own eyes, when God is moſt in their eyes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Learned.</head>
                        <p>A godly unlearned man is better than an ungodly learned man, and a better Scholler.</p>
                        <p>The greateſt Philoſopher that ever was, is but an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:120685:44"/>
ſot to the ſimpleſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
                        <p>A man may know the hiſtory of Chriſt, and yet be ignorant of the myſtery of Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Learning.</head>
                        <p>Learning can onely a dorn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but religion can onely bleſs learning; ſo that learning is more beholding to religion, than religion is beholding to learning.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Leaving Saints.</head>
                        <p>'Tis to be feared, that they, who leave the Saints of God, will not cleave to the God of Saints.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Light, Darkneſs.</head>
                        <p>God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all; and we are dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in us is no light at all; for our light is darkneſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Liking.</head>
                        <p>No man can either like
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:120685:44"/>
all, or be liked of all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Little, Much.</head>
                        <p>Some have the art to make much of their little, but few have the heart to make but little of their much.</p>
                        <p>The little, which but one righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man hath, is better than the riches of many wicked, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37. 16.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Like to God.</head>
                        <p>Chriſtians are not onely like God, but they are alſo liked of God; and Chriſtians do not onely like God, but they ſtudy alſo how to be like God.</p>
                        <p>Some men, inſtead of being like God in this world, are like the God of this world.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Mens Luſts.</head>
                        <p>Mens luſts are their Gods on earth, but they will be their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in hell.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:120685:45"/>
                        <head>Life ſhort.</head>
                        <p>So ſhort and uncertain is our life, that we know not whether he that is born to day may live to day, for as ſoon as a man is born, he begins to die.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Life eternal.</head>
                        <p>Eternal life is begun in this world, for this is eternal life; to know God, and Jeſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent, <hi>John</hi> 13. 3.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Living by Faith.</head>
                        <p>We live by faith, and not by ſight, yet faith is ſeeing; it is the evidence of things not ſeen; for by faith we ſee the things that are not yet ſeen, but ſhall be, when we live by faith and not by ſight.</p>
                        <p>Man lives by death, for his natural life is preſerved by the death of the creature, and his ſpiritual life by the death of Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:120685:45"/>
                        <head>Living to God.</head>
                        <p>They that live to God here, ſhall live with God hereafter, but they that live to the Devil here, ſhall live with the Devil hereafter.</p>
                        <p>He lives long who lives well, for time miſpent is not lived but loſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Living in ſin.</head>
                        <p>They who live moſt in ſin, and in moſt ſin, are moſt dead in ſin.</p>
                        <p>All men live, move, and have their being in God; and yet moſt men are without God, and ſtrangers to the life of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Live.</head>
                        <p>A Saint had rather live at Gods determination, than at his own choice; his prayer is, <hi>Lord chuſe my heritage for me.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:120685:46"/>
                        <head>Loſſes.</head>
                        <p>A Chriſtian gaines by all his loſſes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Love.</head>
                        <p>He doth not faithfully love, who loves not faithfulneſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gods love.</head>
                        <p>God loves his people, even in their ſinful eſtate, though not with a love of well-liking in them, yet with a love of well-willing to them.</p>
                        <p>True love is not onely pleas'd with the beloved, but ſeeks alſo how to pleaſe the beloved.</p>
                        <p>The love of God is better than wine, and his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs better than life and wine; yea, life is the better for the love, and the loving kindneſs of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sick of love.</head>
                        <p>To be ſick of love for God is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120685:46"/>
ſoul-ſaving health; but to be ſick of love for creatures, doth oft deſtroy the health both of body and ſoul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Lovely.</head>
                        <p>There is nothing lovely but what is in Chriſt, and there is nothing in Chriſt but what is lovely.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-Love.</head>
                        <p>Self-love makes a man lovely in his own eyes, but loathſome in Gods eyes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="m" type="part">
                     <head>M</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Magiſtrates.</head>
                        <p>What gain will it be to men to ſave themſelves here, and to loſe themſelves for ever? To live and raign like Gods on earth, and not to live and raign with God in heaven.</p>
                        <p>Many men ſeek other mens goods more than other mens
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120685:47"/>
good, and the wealth of the Commons more than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: but ſuch ſhould conſider, that other mens goods will never be good to other men.</p>
                        <p>When Mageſtrates hearts are not towards the people, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts will not be towards the Mageſtrates.</p>
                        <p>It cannot be expected, that they will be careful of others good, who are careleſs of their own good.</p>
                        <p>Men ſhould order their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſtate by religion, and not religion by reaſons of ſtate.</p>
                        <p>Civill honours are very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in a State, for thereby the State it ſelf becomes more honourable.</p>
                        <p>'Tis a ſad thing when State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men grow richer, but the ſtates
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120685:47"/>
of men, and mens eſtates grow poorer thereby. Such States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould rather follow the noble example of the <hi>Aelian</hi> family, who choſe rather to live poor in a rich Common-wealth, than to live rich in a poor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
                        <p>'Tis but reaſon, that they who bring gain to a State, ſhould gain by the State; provided, that what they gain by it prove not a loſs to it.</p>
                        <p>Some men, when God lifts them up, are lifted up; and whereas advancement ſhould make men lowly, it uſually makes them (or rather they make themſelves) lofty: but men in high places ſhould not be high minded, leaſt he that advanced them up to heaven throw them down to hell.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:120685:48"/>
                        <head>Miniſters.</head>
                        <p>Miniſters ſhould not preach ſounding words ſo much as ſound word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, leaſt ſound preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be turned into a ſound of preaching.</p>
                        <p>They can but badly make God known, who know not God; or they teach Chriſt, who have not learned Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>Men may ſpeak of grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, but God onely can ſpeak grace into us.</p>
                        <p>If the feet of them that bring glad tidings are ſo beautiful, how beautiful are the glad tidings which their feet bring?</p>
                        <p>Many men, yea (alas!) too many good men do the Lords work negligently; but many others (bad men) do altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect to doe the Lords works.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="79" facs="tcp:120685:48"/>
Every man ſhould ſerve God in his vocation, and ſome, whoſe vocation it ſhould be to ſerve God; as all ſhould do it, ſo ſome ſhould do nothing elſe.</p>
                        <p>Its a great ſhame, if all that are Prophets are not the Lords people, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 15. but its a groſſer error to think, that all the Lords people are miniſterial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets. Their being the Lords people makes them fit to hear, but not fit to preach; fit ſheep, but not fit ſhepherds, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4; 5.</p>
                        <p>It was <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s ſin, to make Prieſts of the loweſt and baſeſt of the people, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 3. but it is a greater ſin, to make Prieſts the loweſt and baſeſt of people.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Man made, ſaved.</head>
                        <p>God that made man without
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:120685:49"/>
himſelf, will not ſave man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf.</p>
                        <p>Indeavours without God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, God without indeavours will not ſave any man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Marriage.</head>
                        <p>They that marry where they do not love, will love where they do not marry.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Man of Sin.</head>
                        <p>Though the man of ſin pray to others; yet the man of God will pray to none but to the God of man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Men.</head>
                        <p>The beſt of men are but men at beſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. altogether va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
                        <p>Men are not onely heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, but helliſh alſo by nature.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Meanes.</head>
                        <p>Meanes without God can doe nothing, but God without
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:120685:49"/>
meanes can doe any thing.</p>
                        <p>To truſt in meanes is to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect God, to neglect meanes is to tempt God.</p>
                        <p>The great meanes which God affords his people here, is but little to that which he means to give them hereafter.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Malice, Love.</head>
                        <p>Love excuſeth what is ill done in another; but malice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth what is well done in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Meats.</head>
                        <p>Meats were not forbidden becauſe they were unclean, but were unclean becauſe they were forbidden.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Maſters.</head>
                        <p>If Maſters take none, or but a ſmall account of their Servants, their Servants will make but a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:120685:50"/>
ſmall or none account of their Maſters.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Living Martyrs.</head>
                        <p>How many living Martyrs have willingly ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and yet have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered nothing in their ſufferings, but have taken joyfully the ſpoiling of their goods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they have in heaven a better and an induring ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Miſery of great ones.</head>
                        <p>This is the miſery of the great ones, that their greatneſs will not let them ſee, how little, how nothing, both they and their greatneſs are.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Meetings.</head>
                        <p>Chriſtian meetings are things meet for Chriſtians.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:120685:50"/>
                        <head>Mercy.</head>
                        <p>The price of mercy is to prize mercy.</p>
                        <p>He can never truly reliſh the ſweetneſs of Gods mercy who never taſted the bitterneſs of his own miſery.</p>
                        <p>The depths of mans miſery are not ſo deep as the depth of Gods mercy.</p>
                        <p>Many men take much mercy from God, who are but little taken with the mercies of God, and with the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
                        <p>Such men have no mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own ſouls, who will not receive Gods mercy into their ſouls.</p>
                        <p>God doth not ſhew mercy to his Creatures, becauſe they pleaſe him, but becauſe mercy pleaſeth him; the pleaſuring of them is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:120685:51"/>
the pleaſing of himſelf.</p>
                        <p>'Tis a choice mercy to have the choice of mercies, as <hi>Solomon</hi> had.</p>
                        <p>Riches of mercy are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to encourage men to the commiſſion of ſin, but that they may be incouraged to hope for the remiſſion of ſin.</p>
                        <p>Whoſoever brings mercy, both the mercy and the bringer are both of Gods ſending.</p>
                        <p>They that will not in the day of mercy receive mercy without judgement, ſhall in the day of judgement receive judgement without mercy.</p>
                        <p>God ſhould be the dearer to his people for their mercies, and dearer than their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
                        <p>Almoſt all, or moſt of all Gods juſtice is but mercy, and all our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:120685:51"/>
mercy is but juſtice; for we are all mutual debtors to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but God to none.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Mercies.</head>
                        <p>We then ſeek mercies right, when we ſeek them more to pleaſe God with them, than to pleaſure our ſelves with them.</p>
                        <p>If mercies that come from God are ſo ſweet; how ſweet is God from whom the mercies come? or if mercies that are ſweetned by God are ſo ſweet, how ſweet is God by whom the mercies are ſweetned?</p>
                        <p>God doth not any time put off his people, becauſe he is not in a capacity to give mercy, but doth many times put them off, becauſe they are not in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to receive mercy.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Mercifull.</head>
                        <p>He that is mercifull to the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:120685:52"/>
Saints for Chriſts ſake, ſhall be rewarded by Chriſt for the Saints ſake.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Miracles.</head>
                        <p>God doth not alwayes bind miracles to faith, nor faith to miracles; God will ſometimes be beleived without them, and ſometimes ſpends them upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Money.</head>
                        <p>Onely money well and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gotten is good and lawful money</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Morality.</hi> See <hi>Civility. Mourning.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>A godly man doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mourn in ſecret for his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſinnes, but he alſo mournes in publick for his ſecret ſinnes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="n" type="part">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:120685:52"/>
                     <head>N</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Nature, Grace.</head>
                        <p>Nature teacheth us to prefer our lives before the world, and grace teacheth us to prefer our ſouls before our lives.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Naturall, Spiritual.</head>
                        <p>Natural men will not do all they can; ſpiritual men cannot do all they will.</p>
                        <p>We call fools naturals; but we may (and more truly) call natural men fools.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Natural defects.</head>
                        <p>Natural defects are not the Creatures fault, but the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors pleaſure, and therefore he that finds fault with them, finds fault with God.</p>
                        <p>That man hath a very ill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture who would have others be good to him, but he himſelf loves not to be good to others.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:120685:53"/>
                        <head>Nothing.</head>
                        <p>There is a time when nothing, a time when ſomething, but no time when all things are to be ſpoken.</p>
                        <p>That man hath nothing who wants Chriſt, and that man, who hath Chriſt, wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="o" type="part">
                     <head>O</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Obedience.</head>
                        <p>'Tis obedience to diſobey parents, when we cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them without diſobeying God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Offring.</head>
                        <p>The Offrings did not, nor doe ſanctifie the Altar, but the Altar did and doth ſanctifie the Offring.</p>
                        <p>Vain Offrings are offered in vain; or they that worſhip God vainly do worſhip God in vain,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:120685:53"/>
'tis to no purpoſe, 'tis nothing worth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Omiſſion, Commiſſion.</head>
                        <p>Omiſſion of good is comiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of evill.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>One of Chriſts.</head>
                        <p>'Tis a great mercy to be one of Chriſts, though but one of his little ones.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Orders of Men.</head>
                        <p>In all orders of men, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part are out of order.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Ordinances.</head>
                        <p>Many uſe the Ordinances of God, who make no uſe of them; 'tis indeed good to uſe them, but the gain and ſweetneſs is in making good uſe of them.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt certainly ſpeaks to men in that miniſtry which ſpeaketh men into Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>'Tis to be feared, that they, who turn their backs upon the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:120685:54"/>
Ordinances of God, will at laſt turn their backs upon the God of Ordinances.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Opinion.</head>
                        <p>Moſt men have a good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own opinion, though the opinion be not good.</p>
                        <p>To maintain an opinion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its thine, and not becauſe it is true, is to maintain thy ſelf, not the truth, and ſo to prefer thy ſelf above the truth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Opportunity.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to want opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities for our hearts to improve, than to want an heart to improve our opportunities.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Over-valuing ſelf.</head>
                        <p>He that over values himſelf, is uſually undervalued by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:120685:54"/>
                        <head>Old, New Teſtament.</head>
                        <p>In the old Teſtament the new was vailed, in the new the old is revealed.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="p" type="part">
                     <head>P</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Pardon.</head>
                        <p>God doth not onely give pardon to them that believe, but he alſo gives faith to believe pardon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Parentage.</hi> See <hi>Vice. Parts.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>'Tis not the beſt part of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians excellency, that he is of excellent parts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Paſs-time.</head>
                        <p>That is the beſt paſs-time, wherein the time is beſt paſſed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Peace holding.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to hold ones peace, than by ſpeaking to offend, or to give an offence.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="92" facs="tcp:120685:55"/>
                        <head>Phyſicians.</head>
                        <p>Phyſicians of greateſt value are of no value in ſome caſes; but one may ſay of them, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable comforters are ye all.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Pleaſing God.</head>
                        <p>As what Saints have pleaſeth not God, if offered without themſelves; ſo what they have from God doth not pleaſe them without himſelf.</p>
                        <p>The beſt way to pleaſe all, or diſpleaſe any with leaſt danger, is to pleaſe him, who is all in all.</p>
                        <p>There is nothing ſo ſweetly pleaſing, and pleaſantly ſweet to a gratious heart, as to pleaſe God.</p>
                        <p>A Saint doth not onely ſeek to pleaſe God, but alſo to be pleaſed with God, not onely that his doings may be acceptable to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:120685:55"/>
God, but alſo that all Gods dealings may be acceptable to him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Paſſionate.</head>
                        <p>When others are paſſionate towards Saints, Saints ſhould be compaſſionate towards them.</p>
                        <p>Paſſion makes them fools, which otherwiſe are not ſo; and ſhews them to be fools which are ſo.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Poor, Rich.</head>
                        <p>'Tis the miſery of the poor to be neglected of men, 'tis the miſery of the rich to neglect God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Pride.</head>
                        <p>God will ſtain the pride of all glory, for indeed all pride will ſtain his glory.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Prayer.</head>
                        <p>Prayers not felt by us are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome heard by God.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="94" facs="tcp:120685:56"/>
In prayer a Chriſtian muſt not tell God what he ſhall give, but ask God what he will give.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſhould watch unto prayer, becauſe of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary the Devil, who watcheth him when and whereſoever he prayes.</p>
                        <p>Prayer is like <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s bow, which ſent out the arrows, but faith is like <hi>Ionathan</hi>'s boy, which fetcht back the arrows.</p>
                        <p>The Saints fare the better, yea, are far the better for one anothers prayers.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt doth not dehort us from ſpeaking much, but from much ſpeaking in prayer.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian ſometimes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have what he wants, and other times, yea, often at the ſame time he prayeth to want that he hath.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:120685:56"/>
                        <head>Wordleſs Prayers.</head>
                        <p>An heart without words, is better than words without an heart, in the duty of prayer.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Prayerful, Praiſeful.</head>
                        <p>He that is prayerful before mercy is received, ſhould be praiſeful when he hath received mercy.</p>
                        <p>The returns of prayer call for the return of praiſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Prayerleſs.</head>
                        <p>The prayerleſs man is a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Praiſe.</head>
                        <p>A man ſhould not praiſe his works, but his works ſhould praiſe him.</p>
                        <p>'Tis more a mercy to praiſe God for the mercies we have, than to have mercies to praiſe God for.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:120685:57"/>
                        <head>Practiſe.</head>
                        <p>'Tis good to profeſs, but practiſe is better; yea, of the two, practiſe without profeſſion is better than profeſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out practiſe.</p>
                        <p>Men cannot practiſe unleſs they know, but as good they knew not unleſs they practiſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Precept, Example.</head>
                        <p>Precepts without examples bind more than examples with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out precepts, though examples are more prevailing than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Proud.</head>
                        <p>God reſiſteth the proud, but (giveth grace to, that is) aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the humble.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Portion.</head>
                        <p>The Lords portion is his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Lord is his peoples portion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:120685:57"/>
                        <head>Promiſes.</head>
                        <p>God makes good all the good promiſes which he makes.</p>
                        <p>Wicked men may apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the promiſes, but godly men may apply the promiſes to themſelves.</p>
                        <p>God doth not onely give his people promiſes to believe, but doth alſo give them to beleive the promiſes.</p>
                        <p>Many good promiſes are made, which are not made good.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Profeſſion.</head>
                        <p>'Tis not the onely profeſſion of a Chriſtian, to make onely a profeſſion.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not the profeſſion, but poſſeſſion of Chriſt, which is our hope of glory.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Prophet.</hi> See <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>A Prophet may teach us, but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:120685:58"/>
onely God can teach us to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Providence.</head>
                        <p>Providence is creation conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, or a creation in a new edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="q" type="part">
                     <head>Q</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Quarrell not with God.</head>
                        <p>If God be better to others than he is to thee, yet while God is better to thee than thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt, thou haſt no cauſe to complain.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Queſtions.</head>
                        <p>Of all queſtions, there are two queſtions moſt neceſſary for a people to ask, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable for a Miniſter to reſolve them in.</p>
                        <p>The one is, what ſhall I do to be ſaved?</p>
                        <p>The other, how ſhall I know, that I ſhall obtain ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="r" type="part">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:120685:58"/>
                     <head>R</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Raſh men.</head>
                        <p>Raſh men are commonly harſh men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Receiving Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>They who receive not Chriſt in the acceptable day of the Lord, will not be acceptable to God in the day of the Lord.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Religion.</head>
                        <p>True religion takes moſt from the Creature, and gives moſt to God.</p>
                        <p>Men may differ in religion, and yet be of the ſame religion; for every difference in religion, is not a differing religion.</p>
                        <p>All other (which of a truth are falſe) religions, teach ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by the work of man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, but our (which indeed, and which onely is the true) religion, teacheth ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:120685:59"/>
as a work of God towards man, and in man.</p>
                        <p>He is not learned in religion, who knows all the matters that ought to be known, but he who knows them in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, how they ought to be known.</p>
                        <p>The uſe of the world takes many a man off from religion; religion takes no man off from the uſe, but onely from the abuſe of the world.</p>
                        <p>In religion not to do as thou ſayeſt, is to un-ſay thy religion in thy deeds, and to undo thy ſelf by doing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Reaſon.</head>
                        <p>Reaſon it ſelf will dictate ſo much, that the myſteries of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould be above reaſon; for could a man by reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God and his wayes,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:120685:59"/>
(which are unſearchable) he might think it reaſon, and no robbery, to think himſelf as much a God as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                        <p>Reaſon and faith may walk together, provided, that reaſon give faith the upper hand.</p>
                        <p>Reaſon is not equall in all men, nor perfect in any man, but ſo weak, ſickle and inconſtant in the moſt of men, that as there is no reaſon why any man ſhould lean to his own underſtanding, and there is none or little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why any man ſhould impoſe on another, he being ſo ſeldome and ſo little while conſiſtent with himſelf, who was as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the opinion wherein he was, as he is of the opinion wherin he is.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:120685:60"/>
                        <head>Remiſſion.</head>
                        <p>God doth not onely give remiſſion of ſin to them that repent, but he alſo giveth them repentance for remiſſion of ſins, and gives them to repent of the ſins remitted.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Reſt laboured for.</head>
                        <p>In this world the Saints labour for reſt; but in the world to come they ſhall reſt from their labour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Reproof.</head>
                        <p>Reproof ſhould not be with paſſion, but with compaſſion; not with jearing, but grieving; I tell you theſe things (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> not laughing but weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                        <p>He that reproves anothers fault, and approves his own, is an Hypocrite.</p>
                        <p>Reproofs ſhould not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:120685:60"/>
though they ſhould not be born.</p>
                        <p>Many men are ſo forward to reprove, that they reprove others for ſinning, before they prove that that, for which they reprove them, is a ſin.</p>
                        <p>'Tis the wiſdom of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover to reprove well, that the reproof may take; and 'tis the wiſdom of the reproved, to take the reproof well.</p>
                        <p>'Tis the part of a good man to reprove, though his reproof ſhould not be taken in good part.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Repentance.</head>
                        <p>Some men there are, that repent of their ſins, but forſake them not; others that forſake their ſins, but repent not of them; others (who onely are truly penitent) repent of them,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:120685:61"/>
and forſake them too.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt did die, not onely to give life to them that repent, but alſo to give them repentance unto life; not onely to give ſalvation to them that believe, but alſo to give them to believe unto ſalvation.</p>
                        <p>Some men ſo repent of their ſin, that they ſin in their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo that their very repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is to be repented of.</p>
                        <p>Repentance for ſin is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, without repentance (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning) from ſin.</p>
                        <p>Many men do nothing elſe but make work for repentance, and yet do nothing leſs than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their works.</p>
                        <p>In the repentance of a grave Saint there is much in a little, but in the repentance of a Babe, there is but little in much.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="105" facs="tcp:120685:61"/>
                        <head>Reſurrection.</head>
                        <p>The glory of the Sun finds a reſurrection, how much more then the Sons of glory?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Revenge.</head>
                        <p>Though God ſuffers his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not to ſin in revenging their adverſaries; yet God ſuffers not their adverſaries to ſin unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged.</p>
                        <p>To revenge a wrong done, is to do a wrong to God; ſo a man becomes guilty of that which he complaines of; and therefore unjuſtly complaines of that which he himſelf doth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Reward.</head>
                        <p>Though we ſhould not ſerve God for a reward, yet we ſhall have a reward for our ſervice.</p>
                        <p>Though our reward be not for our good works, yet we ſhall have our good works rewarded,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:120685:62"/>
and have a good reward for our works.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Riches.</head>
                        <p>Riches and the increaſe of riches are neither evils nor dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, unleſs that when they are given to us we give our ſelves to them.</p>
                        <p>If you can ſay, 'tis certain I am rich, I can ſay, 'tis more certain, that your riches are uncertain.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Rich men.</head>
                        <p>Few rich men are godly, but all godly men are rich.</p>
                        <p>Its to be feared, that they that care not how rich they be, or how much riches they get, do not much care how they be rich, nor how they get their riches.</p>
                        <p>Its very likely, that they who enrich themſelves with other
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:120685:62"/>
mens riches, will be ruined by their riches; for other mens goods will never be good to other men.</p>
                        <p>Rich men need poor mens labours, as much as poor men need rich mens money.</p>
                        <p>The rich ſhould not deſpiſe the poor; for God made them both. And he that made thee the rich man, and him the poor man, could have made him the rich man, and thee the poor man.</p>
                        <p>'Tis more honour to be rich in goodneſs, than to be r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ch in goods.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Righteouſneſs.</head>
                        <p>Though beleivers are not to work for righteouſneſs, yet they are to work righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                        <p>Chriſt is the righteouſneſs of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:120685:63"/>
ſinners unto God, and the righteouſneſs of God unto ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Rome.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Rome</hi> would prove the truth by miracles, when it ſhould prove the miracles by truth.</p>
                        <p>It will not be long ere Jeſus Chriſt makes <hi>room</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf; and it will not be long after the deſtruction of the man of ſin, that the ſin of man ſhall be deſtroyed, as ſome think.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Running after Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>When we run after Chriſt, he doth not run from us, yet many times when we run from Chriſt, he runs after us.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="s" type="part">
                     <head>S</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sabbath.</head>
                        <p>Man was not made for the Sabbath, but the Sabbath was made for man.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="109" facs="tcp:120685:63"/>
Some perſons do formally ſerve God on the ſeventh day, but do really ſerve the Devil and ſin all the ſeven dayes; they pretend to keep a Sabbath to God, but ſpend the week, all the week in the devils ſervice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Safe.</head>
                        <p>No man is ſafe among his friends without God, but with God a man is ſafe, though without his friends, and among his enemies.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Saints excellency.</head>
                        <p>All the Saints are excellent, and ſome are more excellent than others; yet the higheſt Saint is not ſo far above the loweſt, as the loweſt Saint is above the higheſt of men.</p>
                        <p>Every Saint is like God in a degree, though not in a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet he is like God in a
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:120685:64"/>
perfection of ſincerity, though not of degrees.</p>
                        <p>God expects that Saints ſhould do more for him than for others, becauſe God hath done more for them than for others.</p>
                        <p>Though it ſads us that he is no better, yet it glads him that he is no worſe.</p>
                        <p>The world ſees not a Saint though they look him in the face, for the Saint is the hidden man of the heart, or the man in the Spirit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Seeking.</head>
                        <p>Though that which thou ſeekeſt for be good, yet while the way by which thou ſeekeſt for it be evill, thou ſhameſt the end by the way and (by the way) wilt thou ſhame thy ſelf in the end.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="111" facs="tcp:120685:64"/>
                        <head>Self-ſeeking.</head>
                        <p>Many men do but ſeek them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſeeking God; and ſerve him, that they may ſerve themſelves of him.</p>
                        <p>Fleſh is the Anagram of ſelf, and in Scripture its all one, to walk after the fleſh, and to ſeek ones ſelf; if then men walk after the fleſh they ſhall die, for every mans perdition is of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-ſearching.</head>
                        <p>It concernes all men to ſearch themſelves, and that quickly, but withall to take heed, they be not ſo quick in ſearching, as not to ſearch to the quick.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Secret.</head>
                        <p>They who are moſt with God in Secret, know moſt of Gods ſecrets.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:120685:65"/>
                        <head>Seeing God.</head>
                        <p>'Tis good to ſee God in all things, and all things in God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Scriptures.</head>
                        <p>We may do well enough with the Scriptures, though we had no traditions; but could not do well enough with traditions, if we had not the Scriptures.</p>
                        <p>The Scriptures ſhew us what God hath done for man, and what man is to do for God.</p>
                        <p>Some men try the Scriptures by the Fathers, but men ſhould try the Fathers and all other men by the Scriptures.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Salvation.</hi> See <hi>Worki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>g.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Their ſalvation may be ſure, who yet may not be ſure of their ſalvation,</p>
                        <p>Faith is as clear a proof, that men ſhall be ſaved, as ſalvation is a clear proof that men have beleived.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:120685:65"/>
                        <head>Scorners.</head>
                        <p>They who ſcorn others, are uſually ſcorned by others.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Service.</head>
                        <p>God takes that ſervice moſt kindly, which is moſt kindly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sermon.</head>
                        <p>To practiſe the Sermon we hear, is the beſt way of repeating the Sermon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Servants.</head>
                        <p>If we are unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants when we have done our duties; how unprofitable are we when we do not do our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</p>
                        <p>When we have done our duty we are but unprofitable ſervants, for our beſt is ſo bad, and our all ſo little, that it is but little more than nothing at all.</p>
                        <p>Though the beſt of men
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:120685:66"/>
(they being at the beſt but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants) deſerve nothing at the hands of God, yet they may deſerve much at the hands of man, and if they have not the recompence which they deſerve, yet 'tis a kind of recompence to have deſerved.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sanctified.</head>
                        <p>The Saints even in this life are ſanctified throughout, (that is) in every part, though every part be not throughout ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sufferings.</head>
                        <p>'Tis an high ſtrain of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alneſs in the ſufferings we bear, or in our bearing ſufferings, when we can ſay, though I love not that which I ſuffer, and though I love not the burden I bear, yet I love to bear the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="115" facs="tcp:120685:66"/>
There are many that ſuffer long, who are not long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Satan accuſing.</head>
                        <p>Satan the great accuſer, doth not onely accuſe the Brethren unto God, but doth alſo accuſe God unto the Brethren.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sin.</head>
                        <p>The induſtrious man hath no leiſure to ſin, the idle man hath no leiſure to avoid ſin.</p>
                        <p>Its one thing to ſin, another thing to be overtaken with ſin, another to be overcome by ſin.</p>
                        <p>Private ſins are oft puniſht with publick ſhame.</p>
                        <p>Every man brought ſin enough into the world to repent of all his dayes, though he ſhould never actually ſin, and ſins enough actually every day to ſorrow
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:120685:67"/>
for, though he had brought none with him into the world.</p>
                        <p>Sin will prove that ſinners downfall, who falls not down to confeſs his ſin, and to give glory to God.</p>
                        <p>The ſin of man filled the Creature with vanity, and the vanity of the Creature fills man with vexation of Spirit.</p>
                        <p>Nothing diſgraceth a man ſo much as ſin, and nothing honours a man ſo much as grace.</p>
                        <p>Some men, when they have prayed againſt ſin, go and ſin againſt prayer.</p>
                        <p>The greateſt of ſins repented of is pardonable; and the leaſt of ſins not repented of is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
                        <p>Great ſinnes forgiven by
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:120685:67"/>
God, muſt not be forgotten by us.</p>
                        <p>God doth not onely take off ſin from his people (which is juſtification) but God takes his people off from ſin (which is ſanctification.)</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sin, Sinners.</head>
                        <p>It ſtands with the juſtice of God, to viſit man with a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual penalty, who, if he might, would live perpetually in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
                        <p>The wicked ſin but for a time, becauſe they live but for a time: By their good wills they would never die, that they might ever ſin, for they ſhew they would ever live in ſin, becauſe they never leave ſinning ſo long as they live.</p>
                        <p>Although the loweſt beleiver is above the power of ſin, yet
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:120685:68"/>
the higheſt beleiver is not above the confeſſion of ſin, becauſe not above the practice of ſin.</p>
                        <p>Every ſin againſt God is great, becauſe it is againſt a great God.</p>
                        <p>When our ſin is increaſed, Gods grace is not decreaſed; though we may be worſe than we were, yet God is as good as ever he was.</p>
                        <p>Nothing deforms a man ſo much as ſin; nothing reforms or adorns a man ſo much as grace.</p>
                        <p>Many men ſee the evills of their ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, who do not ſee the ſin of their evils.</p>
                        <p>Many men ſin with content, and are not content with ſin.</p>
                        <p>By reaſon of our ſins we have cauſe to be ſorrowful in the midſt of our joyes; but by
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:120685:68"/>
reaſon of Gods mercy we have cauſe to rejoyce in the midſt of our ſorrows.</p>
                        <p>A Chriſtian hates ſin for ſins ſake, and forſakes ſin for Gods ſake.</p>
                        <p>The evill of ſin will never deliver us from, but alwayes deliver us to the evill of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sinners.</head>
                        <p>Scarlet ſinners may by grace be made milk-white Saints.</p>
                        <p>The vileſt ſinners, once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, become the ſtricteſt Saints.</p>
                        <p>'Tis better being in hell with Chriſt, than in heaven with ſin.</p>
                        <p>If ſinners caſt not away their ſins for Gods ſake, God will caſt them away for their ſinnes ſake.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:120685:69"/>
                        <head>Singing Saints.</head>
                        <p>In heaven the Saints ſhall ſing notes of the higheſt ſtrains, but they ſhall not ſtrain for the higheſt notes; here their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are noted with <hi>Selah,</hi> there their prayers ſhall be a note above <hi>Elah.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Soul and Body.</head>
                        <p>In this world the body was firſt, and then the ſoul; but in heaven the ſoul is firſt, and then the body.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sorrow.</head>
                        <p>Sorrow for ſin is to laſt as long as there is any ſin to ſorrow for.</p>
                        <p>A true Chriſtian had rather that Chriſt ſhould take away his ſin, and leave his ſorrow, than take away his ſorrow, and leave his ſin.</p>
                        <p>That ſorrow for ſin that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:120685:69"/>
keeps us from beleiving and rejoycing in Chriſt, is ſinful ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
                        <p>Though it be a Chriſtians ſorrow, that he hath ſin to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail; yet his joy, that he hath an heart to bewail his ſin.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Sons of God.</head>
                        <p>Gods Sons are his Servants, and his Servants are his Sons.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Speech.</hi> See <hi>Complement. Spending.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He that when he ſhould not ſpends too much, ſhall when he would not have too little to ſpend.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Succeſs.</head>
                        <p>Succeſs is the bleſſing of God on a good cauſe, and is curſe on a bad cauſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Suffering.</head>
                        <p>'Tis leſſe painful to ſuffer than to ſin, for one may ſuffer
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:120685:70"/>
without ſin, but one cannot ſin without ſuffering.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Superſtitious.</head>
                        <p>Superſtitious men do not fear God, but are afraid of God.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="t" type="part">
                     <head>T</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Teſtament.</hi> See <hi>Old. Temptation.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>He that can repell the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gain, gains by the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
                        <p>The Saints ſhall not be tempted above what they are able; at leaſt not above that which God will enable them to bear.</p>
                        <p>If God do not take off temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from his people, yet he will not ſo keep them, as that temptations ſhall not take them off from him.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="123" facs="tcp:120685:70"/>
                        <head>Thanksgiving.</head>
                        <p>In thankſgiving heart-ſtrings and tongue-ſtrings ſhould be tun'd to our ſoules.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Things.</head>
                        <p>He hath all things who hath God, though he have nothing elſe; but he hath nothing, who hath not God, though he have all things elſe.</p>
                        <p>Thoſe things which have much of our affections, when we have them, coſts us much affliction when we are without them.</p>
                        <p>The ſweetneſs of divine things, is not in the hearing, or praying for, or talking of, but in the having and enjoyment of them.</p>
                        <p>A Saint will part with any thing, yea, with all things for Chriſt, but will not part with
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:120685:71"/>
Chriſt for any thing, no not for all things.</p>
                        <p>The beſt things ill uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come bad, and the worſt things well uſed become good.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Earthly Things.</head>
                        <p>A Chriſtian is not unworthy to manage earthly things; but earthly things are unworthy to be managed by a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
                        <p>Earthly things raviſh more in expectation than in fruition, but heavenly things raviſh more in fruition than in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Time.</head>
                        <p>If you would not have time paſſe too faſt, uſe not too much paſs-time.</p>
                        <p>That which many think their loſt time, a Chriſtian often finds his beſt time, and that is his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:120685:71"/>
thinking time.</p>
                        <p>The redemption of time is not in the recalling of it, but in repenting for miſpent time, and in improving the preſent to beſt advantage.</p>
                        <p>Many men ſpend their time and ſtrength in ſeeking that, which when they have found, they find, that it had been better not to have found or ſought it.</p>
                        <p>Mans idle time is the Devils buſie time; therefore the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath more ſervice in one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day; than in many working dayes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Ill Tongues.</head>
                        <p>If ill tongues could make men ill, many, yea, many good men were in ill taking.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Traytors.</head>
                        <p>Traytors alwayes become
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:120685:72"/>
odious, though the treaſon be commodious.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Troubles.</head>
                        <p>Worldly troubles cannot overcome an heavenly peace.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Truſting God.</head>
                        <p>Our truſting of God ſhould not exclude our endeavours, nor our endeavours exclude our truſting of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Truth.</head>
                        <p>We may and ſhould go from men to follow truth, but we may not go from truth to follow men.</p>
                        <p>God doth not onely deliver truth unto his people, but he alſo delivers his people unto truth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Truth receiving.</head>
                        <p>Many men receive the truth, who do not receive it in truth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="127" facs="tcp:120685:72"/>
                        <head>Try, Truſt,</head>
                        <p>Men we try before we truſt, but God we may truſt before we try.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Types.</head>
                        <p>The book of Types in the old Teſtament hath this common with all other books, that the words ſignifie things; but hath this particular end proper to it ſelf, that all the things ſignifie other things.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="v" type="part">
                     <head>V</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Vanity.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Solomons</hi> Tautologies of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are no vain Tautologies.</p>
                        <p>All ſin is vanity, yet (all that is vain, or) all that is vanity is not ſin,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Vertues.</head>
                        <p>Vertues confeſt by foes, and vices confeſt by freinds are commonly true.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="128" facs="tcp:120685:73"/>
A man may love vertue, yet hate grace.</p>
                        <p>Though gold cometh from the earth, none deſpiſeth it; and though droſſes come from the gold, yet none regardeth it: ſo the vertuous coming from mean parentage are honourable; and the vicious coming from noble parentage are contemptible.</p>
                        <p>'Tis better to be famous from a contemptible family, than to be contemptible from a famous family.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Veſſels, Vaſſals.</head>
                        <p>By nature we are the veſſels of ſin, and the vaſſals of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs.</head>
                        <p>The time is coming, when ungodlineſs ſhall be as much proſecuted by juſtice, as in times paſt godlineſs hath been
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:120685:73"/>
perſecuted by injuſtice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</head>
                        <p>He that loves the wages of unrighteouſneſs, will do unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for the wages.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable.</hi> See <hi>Servant. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſound men.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>They are unſound men, that cannot indure ſound preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of.</head>
                        <p>We ſhould uſe that for Gods glory, which God gives us to uſe for our good.</p>
                        <p>Wicked men have but a right to uſe the Creatures, but godly men have a right uſe of the Creatures.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Voice of Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>Chriſts voice is ſweet to the Saints, and Saints voice ſweet to Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="130" facs="tcp:120685:74"/>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing.</head>
                        <p>The non-uſing, is the abuſing of favours.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling.</head>
                        <p>Man would not when he could, and therefore could not when he would enter into para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Vocation.</hi> See <hi>Calling,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="w" type="part">
                     <head>W</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Walking.</head>
                        <p>A gratious heart deſires not onely to walk holily, but alſo to walk wholly with God.</p>
                        <p>He is the beſt Chriſtian (not who talks moſt of God) but who walks moſt with God.</p>
                        <p>He doth not enjoy much of God, who walks not much with God; nor doth, nor can he walk much with God, who doth nor enjoy much of God.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="131" facs="tcp:120685:74"/>
A Chriſtian need to walk circumſpectly, leaſt he give them that are without an occaſion to offend, or them that are within an occaſion of offence.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Waiting.</hi> See <hi>Grace. Gods Warning.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>God warns his people before he ſtrikes them; and warnes them that he may not ſtrike them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Gods Watching.</head>
                        <p>If God watch not over us, and over our watchings, our watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will be in vain.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Saints Wants.</head>
                        <p>When God ſeems to wink at, even then he ſeeth his peoples wants; and when he ſeems to be careleſs, he is then careful of his people warfare.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="132" facs="tcp:120685:75"/>
Some men find the want of comforts; and ſome a comfort in wants.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Warres.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to be at warres with men, and at peace with God, than to be at peace with men, and at warres with God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>War, Peace.</head>
                        <p>The beſt way for Chriſtians to live in continual peace, is to maintain a continual war, and to be alwayes fighting the good fight of faith.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Weak, Strong.</head>
                        <p>When we are weak, we ſee what we are in our ſelves; when we are ſtrong, we ſee what we are in God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Working Salvation.</head>
                        <p>Man is to work out his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:120685:75"/>
for God worketh in him, both to will and to do; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploies:</p>
                        <p>Firſt, that a man without God, neither can nor will ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                        <p>And ſecondly, that God without man doth not ſave any man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Wickedneſs.</head>
                        <p>'Tis the height of wickedneſs, to do ill, and to think it well done.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Wiſdom.</head>
                        <p>Wiſdom is good with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, yea, better without an inheritance, than an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance without wiſdom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </p>
                        <p>The words of wiſdom ſhould be more acceptable to us, than the wiſdom of words.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Self-Wiſe.</head>
                        <p>The ſelf-wiſe are alwayes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:120685:76"/>
moſt ignorant of themſelves.</p>
                        <p>Many think themſelves wiſe, yea, wiſer than others, who indeed are otherwiſe; for the moſt ſelf-wiſe are very fooles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Wicked, Godly.</head>
                        <p>Wicked men are dead while they live; but godly men live when they are dead.</p>
                        <p>Wicked men have what they enjoy but from the providence of God; but godly men have what they enjoy from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God.</p>
                        <p>The wicked man ſaith, what I will is lawful; but the good man ſaith, what is lawfull I will.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Wife.</head>
                        <p>'Tis better to have a Wife without a portion, than a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without a Wife.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="135" facs="tcp:120685:76"/>
They who marry where they like not, and love not, are like to love where they marry not.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Will.</head>
                        <p>God finds in every man a will to work upon, but he finds not (but makes) any man willing to be wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Judas, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> fulfilled Gods will, in be traying and crucifying Chriſt, and ſo ſinned not; but they did it not to fulfill Gods will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but their own, and that was their ſin.</p>
                        <p>That man hath no good will, that wills no good.</p>
                        <p>God will accept the will for the deed, when we are as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe, as to will the deed.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="136" facs="tcp:120685:77"/>
A Chriſtian may deſire that which God wills not, and not ſin in that deſire; and he may ſin in deſiring that which God wills.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not mans free will, but Gods free grace, which makes one man to differ from another in goodneſs.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Women.</hi> See <hi>Young. Word of God.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Some can read the Word of God, who do not underſtand it, and ſome do underſtand it, who cannot read it.</p>
                        <p>The Word of God is not onely a pure, but purifying; not onely a clean, but a cleanſing Word.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="137" facs="tcp:120685:77"/>
'Tis not the word that man ſpeaks, nor the man that ſpeaks the word, which can convert a ſoul.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Word, Works.</head>
                        <p>The word of life is beſt held forth in the works of our life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Word.</head>
                        <p>In many their words are more than their intentions, and their actions leſſe than their words.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Word, Sword.</head>
                        <p>The Word is Gods Sword, and the Spirit is Gods Arme; now (as that famous Captain, that had loſt his ſword, told his enemies) 'tis not ſo much the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:120685:78"/>
ſword as the arme, unleſs the arme of the Lord be revealed, the report will not be beleived. The Spirit can ſave without the Word, but the Word cannot ſave without the Spirit. Bleſſed are they to whom the Goſpel cometh, not onely in word but in power, in the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Words fit.</head>
                        <p>Fit words are better than fine, for fit words are alwayes fine, but fine words are not alwaye fit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Writing.</head>
                        <p>Men ſhould rather do things worthy to be written, than write things worthy to be done, though both are worth the doing.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="139" facs="tcp:120685:78"/>
                        <head>World.</head>
                        <p>'Tis a ſad thing for a man to be taken out of the world by death, before he be taken out of the world by grace.</p>
                        <p>'Tis a mercy to have a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world: but to have the world for a portion is a miſery.</p>
                        <p>He that loves the world much, can love God but little.</p>
                        <p>They will buy the world at too dear a rate, that pay but one ſin for it.</p>
                        <p>The world is not anſwerable to, nor able to anſwer our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations.</p>
                        <p>'Tis not the having the world, nor having an hand in the world, but having an heart in the world, which God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alowes.</p>
                        <p>Be wiſely-worldly, be not worldly-wiſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <pb n="140" facs="tcp:120685:79"/>
                        <head>Works.</head>
                        <p>A Saint doth not ſo much do good works to live, as live to do good works.</p>
                        <p>'Tis better that a mans own works, than that another mans words ſhould praiſe him.</p>
                        <p>The works which many men do, do honour God, when yet the men that do the works may diſhonour God: We work not our ſelves into Chriſt, but Chriſt works us into himſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Worth.</head>
                        <p>That place is worth the look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, which will make one lovely in the eyes of God.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="y" type="part">
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:120685:79"/>
                     <head>Y</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Young Women.</head>
                        <p>If young Women were cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but with the Silk of Piety, the Sattin of Sanctity, and the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Modeſty, God himſelf would be a Suitor to them.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="z" type="part">
                     <head>Z</head>
                     <div type="entry">
                        <head>Zeal.</head>
                        <p>Many men have much zeal, and little knowledge: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, who have much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, have but little zeal.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:80"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AN HOLY ALPHABET FOR YOUNG CHRISTIANS.</p>
                  <p>Being the principall points of Religion, laid down in entire Propoſitions and expreſs words of Scripture for the more Authority.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is annexed, THE FAITHFUL SHEPHEARD, Guiding his FLOCK in a way of walking with God dayly.</p>
                  <p>By ROBERT PORT Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dawſon</hi> for <hi>George Sawbridge,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> upon <hi>Ludgate-hill,</hi> 1658.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:81"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120685:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>AN Holy Alphabet For Young CHRISTIANS.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Principles of Religion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's onely asking the Queſtion, what is? ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereto the firſt words of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and the Propoſition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns you the Anſwer. Inſtance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:120685:82"/>Q. What is Adoption?</p>
                  <div n="a" type="part">
                     <head>A</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A</hi> Adoption is an act of Godsfree Grace, whereby we are received into the number, and have right to all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the ſons of God,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proofe.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 1. <hi>John</hi> 1. 12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="b" type="part">
                     <head>B</head>
                     <p>Baptiſm is a Sacrament, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the waſhing with water, in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, doth ſignifie and ſeal our ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into Chriſt, and partaking of the benifits of the Covenant of Grace, and our engagement to be the Lords,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 27.</p>
                     <p>The Body is the outward and earthly part of Man, made of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120685:82"/>
the begining of the duſt of the earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="c" type="part">
                     <head>C</head>
                     <p>Calling effectuall is the work of Gods ſpirit, whereby convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing us of our ſin and miſery, inlightning our minds in the knowledge of Chriſt, and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our wils, he doth perſwade and enable us to embrace Jeſus Chriſt freely offered to us in the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 1. 9. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 13, 14. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. 18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26, 27. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 44, 45. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
                     <p>Creation, is Gods making all things of nothing, by the word of his power, in the ſpace of ſix daies, and all very good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 2.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="d" type="part">
                     <head>D</head>
                     <p>Decrees of God are, his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal purpoſe, according to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120685:83"/>
councell of his will, whereby for his own glory, he hath fore-ordered whatſoever comes to paſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 4. 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22, 23.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="e" type="part">
                     <head>E</head>
                     <p>Election, is the eternal and unchangeable decree of God, whereby of his free Grace and mercy he hath made choice of ſome rather than others, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon them eternal life and happineſs, and that for the glory of his free grace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 2. 5, 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="f" type="part">
                     <head>F</head>
                     <p>Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, whereby we rejoice and reſt upon him alone for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as he is offered unto us in the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 39. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 3, 4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:120685:83"/>
An holy Faſt, is a religious abſtinance from all the labors of our calling, and comforts of this life, ſo far as comlineſs and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity will permit, that we might be more ſeriouſly humble before God, and more fervent in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Ecle.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 27. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 9. 11.</p>
                     <p>An holy Feaſt, is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary thanksgiving for ſome notable diliverance out of ſome deſperate danger, teſtified with feaſting before God, with joy and gladneſs, ſending Preſents to our friends, and Portions to the needy, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 8 <hi>Chap.</hi> 29. 10, 11. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8, 10. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 9. 22.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="g" type="part">
                     <head>G</head>
                     <p>God is a Spirit, infinite, eternal, and unchangeable in his being, wiſdom, power, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120685:84"/>
juſtice, goodneſs and truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 24. <hi>Iob</hi> 11. 7, 8, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 2. <hi>Ia.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. 5. <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. 4. <hi>Ex.</hi> 34. 6, 7.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="h" type="part">
                     <head>H</head>
                     <p>Holy Ghoſt, is a true and co-eternal God, with the eternal Father and the Son, and is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to me, to make me through a true faith, partaker of Chriſt and all his benefits, to comfort me, and to abide nigh me for ever, <hi>Phil.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 48. 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3, 26. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 34. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Mal.</hi> 23. 19, 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 14. <hi>Acts,</hi> 9. 31. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 26.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="i" type="part">
                     <head>I</head>
                     <p>Jeſus Chriſt is the eternal Son of God, who in time became Man for his Elect, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120685:84"/>
Inſtitution, is an Act of Gods free Grace, wherein he pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all our ſins, and accepteth us as righteous in his ſight, onely for the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us, and received by faith alone, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24, 25. <hi>Chap</hi> 4. 6, 7, 8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19. 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 17, 18, 19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="m" type="part">
                     <head>M</head>
                     <p>Mortification is that grace whereby our natural corruption is ſubdued; and vivification (or quickning) is that grace too, wherby inherent holineſs is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in us, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 22, 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. 11. 13. <hi>Col</hi> 2. 12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="o" type="part">
                     <head>O</head>
                     <p>Obedience now, is a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful endeavour to give unfeigned obedience to all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, according to that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120685:85"/>
of ſtrength, wherewith God doth enable us, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 74, 75. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 2. 5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="p" type="part">
                     <head>P</head>
                     <p>Petition is a prayer, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we deſire the preventing or removing things hurtful, and the obtaining of things needful, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for this life, or that which is to come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 1. to 5.</p>
                     <p>Prayer, is an offering up of our deſires to God for things agreeable to his will, in the name of Chriſt, with confeſſion of our ſins, and thankful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, of his mercies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 8. 1 <hi>Io.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Io.</hi> 10 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 5, 6. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 4. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
                     <p>Gods Providence, is his moſt wiſe, holy, and powerful
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120685:85"/>
preſerving and governing of all his creatures, and all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 24 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 19. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 29. to 31.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="r" type="part">
                     <head>R</head>
                     <p>Reconciliation, is that grace whereby we are freed from Gods curſe, and reſtored to his fatherly favour. <hi>Rom</hi> 3. 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 8, 9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2 16. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
                     <p>Repentance, is a ſaving grace, whereby a ſinner out of a true ſence of his ſin, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the mercy of God in Chriſt, doth with grief and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of his ſin turn from it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, with full purpoſe of, and endeavour after new obedience, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 18. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. 37, 38. <hi>Icel.</hi> 2. 12 <hi>Ier.</hi> 3. 32. <hi>Ch.</hi> 31. 18. 19. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="s" type="part">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:120685:86"/>
                     <head>S</head>
                     <p>A Sacrament is an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance inſtituted by Chriſt; wherein by ſenſible ſigns, Chriſt and the benifits of the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant are repreſented, ſealed, and applied to believers, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. 10. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. 26.</p>
                     <p>Sin, is any want of conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto, or tranſgreſſion of the law of God, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 4.</p>
                     <p>The Soul is the inward and ſpiritual part of Man, which is mortal and never can dye, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 8. <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 9.</p>
                     <p>The Supper of the Lord, is a Sacrament, wherein by giving and receiving bread and wine, according to Chriſts appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his death is ſhewed forth, and the worthy receivers are (not after of a corporal and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120685:86"/>
manner, but) by faith, made partakers of his body and blood with all his benefits, to their ſpiritual nouriſhment and growth in grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. to 27. <hi>Ch.</hi> 10. 16.</p>
                     <p>Sanctification is the work of Gods free Grace, whereby we are renewed in the whole man after the image of God, and are enabled more and more to die unto ſin, and live unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, 2 <hi>Th.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 23, 24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="t" type="part">
                     <head>T</head>
                     <p>Thankſgiving is a prayer, wherein we render thanks to God for his general goodneſs, and particular favours, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 1. to 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="v" type="part">
                     <head>V</head>
                     <p>A Vow religious, is a ſolem
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120685:87"/>
promiſe unto God, made by a fit perſon, of ſome lawfull thing which is in his choice, to reſtifie his love and thankfulneſs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 21, 22. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="w" type="part">
                     <head>W</head>
                     <p>The word of God, is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures imediatly inſpired, which is contained in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:120685:87"/>
                  <head>THE Faithful SHEP HEARD, Guiding his Flock in a way of walking with God dayly.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ndeavour to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of thy original corruption dayly, how it inclines thee to evill, and indiſpoſeth thee to good; groan under it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120685:88"/>
it as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7 24. tk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſpecial notice of your actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſins or dayly infirmities, in thought, word, and deed.</p>
                     <p>Indeavour to make your peace with God for them two waies.</p>
                     <p>I. By repenting them, and confeſſing them to God, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your heart to grieve for them, by ſome melting conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, as of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to you, thy unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unprofitableneſs of ſin, the prejudice and damage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the ſoul, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 9.</p>
                     <p>II. By believing or caſting your ſelf wholly on Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, for the remiſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and reconciliation with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 22, to 26. Cleaving to Gods promiſes of pardon and peace, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 43. 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120685:88"/>
waiting til the Lord ſhal ſpeak to you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. 8.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <p>GEt your union with, and intereſt in Chriſt, cleared and confirmed to you dayly more and more, that you are a branch in his vine, a member in his body, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. This may be done three waies.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. By the dayly renewal of your faith in Chriſt, eſpecially of that act of faith, whereby the ſoul knits or ties it ſelf unto Chriſt, caſts or roules it ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt for ſalvation. Cauſe your heart in a ſolemn manner every day to act this part, or put forth this primitive act of faith in view of the whole ſoul.</p>
                     <p>The dayly exerciſe hereof will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120685:89"/>
increaſe and ſtrengthen the divine habit of faith in the ſoul, and make the ſoul ſenſible of the very act of it; by frequent believing, you ſhall feel at your very heart, that you do believe, ſo ſhall you have a witneſs in your ſelf that you are in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 10.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. By examining your heart upon what grounds you take Chriſt to be yours, and they are five.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. A fight and ſence of your ſins, of the guilt, power, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of them, of your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery by them, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. 13.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Your want of Chriſt ſeen and felt at your very heart, to juſtifie, ſanctifie, redeem, and ſave you, or elſe you are utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt and undone everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 10.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:120685:89"/>
3. Gods free and general of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Chriſt to any that will take him by faith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. manifold promiſes to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The ground of all Gods offers and donations of Chriſt, being free Grace, rich mercy, underſerved love, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 4. to 8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 4. to 7.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Chriſts ſweet and gracious invitation of ſuch to come to him, as are weary of ſin, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11. 28. to buy, as have no money, no righteouſneſs to commend them to Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1. no worth or deſert in themſelves.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. As ſinfull vile wretches as you are, have been bought of Chriſt, and found in Chriſt, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 9. to 12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7. to 10. why may not you? the more clearly you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120685:90"/>
upon what grounds you take Chriſt, the more clear is your title to Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. By ſurveying and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving in what manner you take Chriſt dayly, and this by five reſolves, as</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Whether you do wholly renounce all opinion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of your own righteouſneſs and deſert? <hi>Matt.</hi> 8. 34. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 7 to 10. So that you come to Chriſt empty of your ſelf, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vile, yea nothing in your own eyes, unworthy to receive Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whether you lay hold on Chriſt alone with an empty hand of faith, joyning nothing with Chriſt in the matter of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whether you find the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drawing your heart after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120685:90"/>
Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 44. in hungring panting deſires, that will never be ſatisfied without Chriſt; So that the ſtream both of your judgment, <hi>Phil.</hi> 37. 8. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. run towards Chriſt?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Whether you take Chriſt as a Lord to rule you, as a Jeſus to ſave you, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 6. As one that is all, to your all, your wiſdom, your righteouſneſs, your ſanctification, and redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. your ſpiritual food, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 36. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14. Strength, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 13. Life, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2, 10.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Whether you ſeek and wait for Chriſt (out of the ſence of your ſpiritual penury) ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, prayer, meditation, conference, not as they are your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120685:91"/>
own works of ſanctification, but as they are Gods ordinances appointed of purpoſe for the manifeſtation &amp; communication of Chriſt to the ſoul? frequent peruſal hereof, will clear to you your manner of taking Chriſt, which wil evidence to you, your right in Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <p>LAbour to draw, and derive from Chriſt, by the pulling attractive force of faith, abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſufficient for the day.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. To perform all duties, <hi>Phil,</hi> 4. 12.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. To exerciſe all the graces, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. To reſiſt and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all temptations and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 37.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:120685:91"/>
IIII. To undergo all the trials &amp; afflictions thereof, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 16. Thus make your proviſion of grace and ſtrength from Chriſt every morning, fetch ſo much as you have occaſion to uſe all the day long, yea and upon all occaſions that fall out in the day. Go to Chriſt ſtill for the wisdom that muſt direct you; for the holineſs that muſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter you; for the ſouldier that muſt bear them, if they be croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for that ſtrength that muſt reſiſt them, if they be tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for ability to performe them, if they be duties. To this end, act your faith dayly in the promiſes of grace and ſtrength, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 16. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26, 27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 3 <hi>Zack</hi> 10 12. which are both ſecurity given you by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120685:92"/>
God, that you ſhall receive grace and conduit-pipes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of conveying the ſame from Chriſt unto you. Loe, this is the manner to do all in the ſtrength of Chriſt, and to take forth a great deal of Chriſt into the ſoul, that not you, but Chriſt may live in you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                     <p>Perform daily duties in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cloſet, eſpecially theſe three, Prayer, Meditation, Reading, all with ſerious affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, heat of affection, deligence and delight, <hi>Ier.</hi> 48. 10. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 24. theſe three waies.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Watch to theſe duties, <hi>H. E.</hi> keep thy heart in a good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120685:92"/>
frame for them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 18. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled with ſin, untainted with the world.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. Take the fitteſt time for the performance of them all, when you are the leaſt evil and ſluggiſh: Begin the day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly with thoughts of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Be very reall, ſerious, and ſubſtantial with God in them.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Indeavour to feel all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in your heart, inlivening, enlarging, infleming your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections<hi>:</hi> Theſe be duties of moſt importance and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, commodity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the ſoul, becauſe they properly appear at, and reach at the ſouls good and caeleſtial hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, to train up a ſoul of a Believer for heaven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:120685:93"/>
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <p>FOrtifie your ſelf every morning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſpecial luſts, to which you are by nature moſt prone, or ſhall be moſt tempted; be it pride, paſſion, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, &amp;c. This muſt be done four waies: As,</p>
                     <p n="1">I. By arguments and holy reaſonings within your ſelves, drawn fom the ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof, as diſprofit, diſcomfort, diſgrace &amp;c. to diſcover the unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of your ſin, and make your ſoul aſhamed of it<hi>:</hi> For inſtance. Shall I be proud? Then I am ſure to fall, and God will count me for his enemie, for God reſiſteth the proud, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>am.</hi> 4: 6. Shall I be angry? If I let paſſion in, I cannot keep ſatan out, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 4: 26, 27. I ſhall grieve thereby the holy ſpirit of God, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 4: 30, 31. Shall I be covetous? I cannot but be very ſinful, ſith the love of money is the root of all evil, 1 <hi>Tim;</hi> 6<hi>:</hi> 10.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. By pondring in your minds pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in the Book of God againſt ſuch ſins, judgments threatned, or inflicted <hi>Prov:</hi> 6: 23, 24. on proud <hi>Herod, Acts</hi> 12: 23. voluptuous <hi>Dives, Luke</hi> 16:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120685:93"/>
28. churl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 25<hi>:</hi> 38.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. By applying promiſes of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication cloſe to your hearts, as a plaiſter to the ſore, for ſubduing your iniquity, <hi>Mic:</hi> 7: 19. <hi>Rom:</hi> 6: 14.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. By drawing vertue from Chriſts death into the ſoul, which hath in it a killing force of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6: 4: 107. <hi>Phi.</hi> 4: 10.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                     <p>GEt your heart ſtrongly fixt on God, by truſting on him; <hi>Pſal:</hi> 112: 7. and ſubmitting to him, 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 3<hi>:</hi> 18. againſt all the fears, cares, double trialls, affliction of every day, for ſufficient to the day, is the evill thereof, <hi>Mat:</hi> 6: 34.</p>
                     <p>This muſt be done five waies.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Be prudent to foreſee your perſonal tryals and troubles, what ever they are like to be, <hi>Prov:</hi> 22: 3.</p>
                     <p n="2">II: Go hide and lay up your ſelf in God, run unto his name, for God is a work of habitation, to which a poor ſoul may continually reſort, God will give commandment to ſave him, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 71: 3. 1 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et:</hi> 4: 19.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Eſpecially commit that ver,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120685:94"/>
thing to God, put it into his hands, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you deſire to keep or fear to looſe, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1<hi>:</hi> 12. be it life, liberty, name, friends maintenance, &amp;c. what you would have reſolved if it be a doubt, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 37<hi>:</hi> 5. or ſupply'd if it be a want, removed if it be a croſs, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50<hi>:</hi> 15. and together with the thing caſt all your care, fear, ſorrow, and trouble of mind about it, wholly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, <hi>Matt:</hi> 6: 31. 1 <hi>Pet;</hi> 5, 7: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 55: 22.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Renew your faith in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes every, day, which moſt concerns your preſent ſtate, As,</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. In promiſes of ſupplyes if you be in want, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 34<hi>:</hi> 8. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37: 3. &amp; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84: 11. <hi>Matt:</hi> 6: 30.</item>
                        <item>2 Of direction if in doubts, <hi>Iam:</hi> 1: 5.</item>
                        <item>3. Of deliverance if in trouble, <hi>Iob</hi> 5. 19. Of a good end and ductified uſe of all, <hi>Deut:</hi> 8; 16. <hi>James</hi> 5: 11. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8: 28. <hi>Heb:</hi> 12: 10.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="5">V. Laſtly labour to ſee Gods hand, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34: 9. Believe Gods love, <hi>Heb;</hi> 12: 6. <hi>Rev:</hi> 3: 19. and with all meekneſs &amp; patience to reſign up your ſelf wholly to Gods will in every affliction, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t:</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: 39.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:120685:94"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                     <p>GEt and keep a ſavory, reliſh continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of your Chriſtian priviledges, wherewith you are inveſted as you are new creatures in Chriſt<hi>:</hi> more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of theſe ſix.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Of your dignity, that you are Gods Sons, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3 1, 2. Chriſts brethren, <hi>Heb</hi> 2: 11. Heavens heirs, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20<hi>:</hi> 17. Partakers of an high and heavenly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2: 5.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. Of your liberty, that you are the Lords free men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3: 14. delivered out of the hands of all enemies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7: 22. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17: 39.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Of your victory, that you are through Chriſt more than Conquerors over all the world of creatures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8: 37, 38. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5: 4. of evils, temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, perſecutions.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Of your ſafety, that you have an almighty God for your place of refuge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18<hi>:</hi> 2. an hedg of providence, <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h,</hi> 1<hi>:</hi> 10. a guard of Angels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91<hi>:</hi> 11. an incloſure of mercy, <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>:</hi> 32: 10. and Gods promiſe, as a writ of protection for defence, <hi>Heb:</hi> 13: 5. 6.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:120685:95"/>
V. Of your riches as durable ſubſtance in heaven, <hi>Heb:</hi> 10: 34: an incorruptible inheritance, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1. 4. a kingdom of glory, <hi>Luke</hi> 12: 32. and a crown of life, <hi>Rev:</hi> 2: 10. for you are heirs of God, and co-heirs of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="6">VI. Of your joy and pleaſure, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious for kind and plentiful for meaſure, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 16: 11. peace unconceivable, <hi>Phil:</hi> 4<hi>:</hi> 7. joy unſpeakable, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1: 8. the Maſters joy: O<hi>!</hi> get your hearts affected with all theſe as being yours: Chew and ſuck them by ſerious meditation; work and warm them upon your hearts by cloſe applycation, rubbing them into your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: Oppoſe theſe your ſpiritual pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges to your temporal preſſures, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the one againſt the other, as your heavenly friends to your earthly foes; your high dignity in Chriſt, to your meanneſs in outward condition; your wealth above, to your want below; your future joy and reſt, to your preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and ſorrows: This will not onely make you patient under your afflictions in this life, <hi>Rom:</hi> 12<hi>:</hi> 11. but joyful in them, <hi>Rom:</hi> 5: 3. and triumphant over them, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15<hi>:</hi> 55. Thus did <hi>Paul,</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:120685:95"/>
                        <hi>Rom:</hi> 8: 18. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4: 17. <hi>Chap:</hi> 6: 8, 9, 10. Theſe will provoke to duty, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2: 9, 11, 12. and preſerve from fainting, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4: 16, 17. and from trouble of heart, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14: 1, 2.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                     <p>SAnctifie God in your hearts dayly, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3: 15. make him your fear, <hi>Pſ:</hi> 37<hi>:</hi> 4. To this end do theſe four things.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. Have often high and honourable thoughts of God, ſerious meditations of his glorious attributes, as his wiſdom, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, mercy, juſtice, &amp;c. and work them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your hearts, that they may eccho to thee with pure and melting affections; this will encreaſe and nouriſh up the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature faſt in you, 2 <hi>Pet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> 1: 4.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. Labour to be affected with all the works of God, As,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To behold and admire the works of God, <hi>Iob</hi> 37: 14. in the Creatures, <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> 136: 5.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To ſee and taſt Gods goodneſs in every mercy, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 34. 8.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To take notice of, and tremble at the anger and diſpleaſure of God in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry affliction or judgment, <hi>Pſ:</hi> 119<hi>:</hi> 120.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120685:96"/>
                        <hi>Hab:</hi> 3: 16. That ſo you might anſwer the diſpenſations of Gods providence, with ſuitable deſpoſitions, your hearts carrying a countenance in affection to all Gods actions <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26: 8.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Wreſtle with God by praying and believing, for an heart of fleſh, <hi>Eze:</hi> 36: 26. which will receive impreſſion from the very thoughts of God in the mind.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. Apply promiſes to particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as, 1. Of love, <hi>Deut:</hi> 30: 6. 2. of fear, <hi>Ier:</hi> 32. 40. 3. of delight, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 58: 14. There is heat and life in theſe promiſes ſufficient to quicken and warm thy dead and frozen affections.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                     <p>GEt a publick ſpirit to mind things of Jeſus Chriſt, as rationally as if they were your own things, <hi>Phil:</hi> 2: 30, 31. to look on the things of others, &amp; prefer <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems</hi> welfare before your chiefeſt joy, <hi>Pſ:</hi> 137: 5<hi>:</hi> 6: &amp; the Goſpels liberty before your own, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Acts</hi> 21<hi>:</hi> 13. To mourn for the ſins of the times, as the godly in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did <hi>Ezek:</hi> 9: 4. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially lay to heatt,</p>
                     <p n="1">I. The Churches miſery, when Gods
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120685:96"/>
ordinance go down and heriſie and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition go up; when any thing fals out which gives a blow to Religion, or prove an impediment to the Goſpel, If the Ark be taken, call your comforts Icabods, 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 4<hi>:</hi> 21.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. The afflictions of <hi>Joſeph, Amos,</hi> 6: 6. the ſufferings of Gods ſervants' whether Magiſtrates, Miniſters, or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; O ſimpathize with them, <hi>Heb:</hi> 13: 3. <hi>Nehe:</hi> 1: 4. labour to feel their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and ſorrows at your very hearts, and pray earneſtly for them as the Church did for <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 12: 5.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. The ſigns of the times, which Hipocrites cannot diſcern, though they be well verſt in the face of the sky, <hi>h. e.</hi> The ſad ſimptomes and preſages of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judgments, as theſe ſeven following ſignifies.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The commonneſs of ſin, for all ſorts tranſgreſs, in all kind of open ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with an high hand againſt light and nature, and meanes of grace, <hi>Gen:</hi> 15<hi>:</hi> 15. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 12<hi>:</hi> 3. <hi>Chap:</hi> 22: 4.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Contempt of Gods ordinances, miſuſing of his Miniſters, 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 36: 16.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The departure of Gods glory from his houſe, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 9: 3.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:120685:97"/>
4. Incorriſibleneſs after former, and under preſent judgments, <hi>Levit:</hi> 26: 15.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The death of many righteous men, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 57: 1. The carrying away of others to hiding places.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The Vials of Gods wrath powred upon the Churches beyond the Seas, <hi>Ier:</hi> 17: 12: 14.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. An Inundation of ſpiritual judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as a ſpirit of error, Appoſtacy, ſuperſtition, &amp;c. which do commonly conclude and end in temporal plagues, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 6: 10, 11. Now O Chriſtian! the Holy Ghoſt is a publick ſpirit breathing and acting in all the members of the body miſtical, pray for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 11: 13. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve for it, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3: 14.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X.</head>
                     <p>LAſtly get your heart renewed from the world, and from thoſe creature comforts in it, which are deareſt and ſweeteſt to you, wife, children, friends, goods, liberty, houſe; life, this Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of thoſe that follow him, <hi>Luke</hi> 14: 26, 27. <hi>Mark,</hi> 10: 29 30. This will prepare you either to ſuffer or to die, el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which may put you upon it to love all. To this conſider ſeriouſly theſe four things: As,</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:120685:97"/>
I. All the world and all Creature comforts cannot ſatisfie the heart, when thou haſt injoyed them to the full, <hi>Eccl:</hi> 1: 8. <hi>Chap:</hi> 5: 9, 10. you ſoon grow weary of them, or glutted with them, ſo that you deſire ſome new delights, or more of the old, or ſome over again.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. Nor can they ſaſtisfie you, but expoſe oft to many luſts, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6: 9, 10. temptations, deſtractions, to a ſpirit of the world, and they hinder from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Matt:</hi> 19: 22.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. Nor can they ſave you from Gods wrath, from death or judgment, <hi>Prov:</hi> 11: 4. The wicked whoſe portion is onely here, oft have the greateſt ſhare of them, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 17: 14. <hi>Iob</hi> 21: 7: to 14.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. They ſerve onely for this life, whil'ſt we are on this ſide of the grave, they ſhall not be the leaſt ingredients in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our celeſtial happineſs.</p>
                     <p>O Chriſtians when we come to be happy in heaven, we ſhall ſtand in no need of food, raiment, phyſick, marriage, <hi>Matt:</hi> 22: 30. for we ſhall be like the Angels of God in heaven, we ſhall then hunger no more, nor thirſt any more, <hi>Revel:</hi> 7: 16. we ſhall then and there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120685:98"/>
live by the alſufficient ſpirit of God, which needs no refreſhing; we ſhall be cloathed then with long white robes of immortality, <hi>Revel:</hi> 7: 9. To Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, when we come to heaven (the place of Gods habitation) we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the face and beatifical preſence of the moſt glorious Jehovah (bleſſed for ever) as an object wherein all the powers of our ſouls will be ſatisfied with ineffable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and everlaſtingneſs: God will be to us all in all, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15<hi>:</hi> 28. O come LORD JESUS, Revel. 22: 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120685:98"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
